[Music]
welcome back everyone for the second day
of our
international women's day north america
summit it's great to see you all
tuning in again hope you all enjoyed the
first day sessions with us
if you didn't join the first day my name
is cubra zengin and i'm the regional
lead for google developer groups and
women techmakers programs
for the north america region at google
i'm karina liu also on the north america
developer ecosystem team at google
supporting our google developer groups
and women techmaker communities
hey ty because we have another day
full of inspirational talks and
technical content coming from the
leaders across google
and our committee this iwd summit
wouldn't have been possible without the
dedicated time and effort of our amazing
north america developer community
organizers who have collectively helped
to put together
this two-day event for you all to enjoy
before we jump into the talks
just a quick reminder be excellent to
each other
we want to continue to provide a safe
environment for you to enjoy the
learnings
speakers and networking so for any
reason you have concerns
please let us know there is also the
link shared here to submit a form
just a reminder this is an inclusive
conference with a zero tolerance
for any form of harassment secondly
feel free to share your questions with
the speakers on the chat
they will be answering some of your
questions here
our team will also be available to help
with any questions you may have
also there's a slack group where you can
join to connect and network with other
participants
at this event we also appreciate your
input
so feel free to share your feedback
there are some awesome raffle prizes
that we will
that will be up for grabs that you will
be
interested in to win once you complete
it
and lastly don't forget to use these
hashtags to share your photos and
memorable moments from the event with
us on your socials also have fun
alright who is ready to get started
without further ado
i'm excited to welcome our panel of
women trailblazers
who will be sharing their experiences
and journeys into tech
how they were able to pivot to a new
role chart their own
course and how you can do it too
join us today to welcome alana elise
jeannie julissa and syria who work on
different teams at google
[Music]
hi everyone welcome to our pivot and
career journeys of women in tech panel
i'll be your facilitator today my name
is janine lee
and i'm a global learning and
development manager focused on career
development in the google data center
organization
i'm going to first start with
introducing our panelists today
we have alana karen who's the director
of search platforms
elise burkhoffer global head of women's
community and programs
julissa ramirez technical program member
of google cloud
and surya hughley head of customer
service training and communications for
google fiber
thank you all for being here with us
today as we get started i'd love for
each panelist to just take some time to
share what we call your origin story
so how did you get to your current role
and to the tech world
we'll start with alana i was back in
college
and i was getting really interested in
what was then
just starting back in the day around web
design
and that led me down the road of
practicing that in my spare time and
self-teaching
and then getting my first job as a
webmaster
which then later on led to startups
one of them being google um and i've
been here
19 years now so i've had various roles
all in operations so that's how that's
essentially how i've gotten
in brief to where i am
thank you alana i think you might have
the longest tenure at google for someone
that i've ever met
we're gonna then move on to elise
sure so i grew up in the bay area in
silicon valley
and studied psychology and communication
at stanford and was really fascinated in
how the internet was
changing our world and helping us with
so much innovation so came to google
straight after school
started in our marketing organization
for a number of years and have pivoted
into my current role heading up our
women's community that's amazing thank
you elise and i think we'll want to hear
more about your pivots as we go along
with the panel
we're going to move on to jalisa hi
everyone
uh so i immigrated from the dominican
republic when i was nine years old and
then
grew up in new york city my whole life
moved on and
graduated from my university with an
undergrad in electrical and mechanical
engineering
degree and a master's in manufacturing
mechanical systems
from a school upstate new york rochester
uh then i moved to california where i
started my first job as a manufacturing
engineer
working on a missile longitude program
at northrop grumman
moved on to intel where i spent majority
of my career
and that led me to the tpgm world
and then i started knowing that yes i
love being technical but i also
love enjoying and love and enjoy working
with engineers presenting data to exact
and driving processes to completion and
that led me to my current role
at google as a tpgm in cloud
thank you julissa it sounds like you've
moved around quite a bit and you have a
very interesting background so thank you
for sharing that with us
um and last but not least surya hi
everyone
my career actually started in a very
different space
my undergraduate was actually biology
pre-med
when i made the determination that
medicine was not for me i moved into
environmental sciences
and um during the downturn of economy i
did have
time to think through like what would be
my next steps a decade ago
related to my career which landed me at
uh turner broadcasting which is now
warner media
where i was responsible for in the
learning and development space
technology training programs for 17 000
employees
i did that for a little while and then
all things google
interests me related to learning and
development because of my true passion
for people
learning and i felt that google
understood that
um so a few years ago i started at
google fiber
to where i built up brick and mortar for
25 000 square foot training facility to
train on all things google fiber
through promotions and pivots changes
my role has changed and in a great way
i now lead the learning and development
team for a few channels across google
fiber
along with customer service and it's
been a great journey
amazing surya i think we share the same
passion for learning and development so
thank you for being here today
all right we're going to get started
with some of our first questions
so you've all become leaders at one of
the top tech companies in the world
which itself is really difficult
but on top of that you'd have to work
your way up into a space where women are
disproportionately underrepresented in
tech
what has that journey been and how did
you navigate that
syria would you like to kick us off
absolutely so
coming out of a corporate space before i
joined technology
um you know there's always that
hierarchy of white males and so i
learned how to navigate
outside of a technology space so when it
came into a technology space i thought
that i could navigate the same
and that um just come in lead your teams
do a great job set priorities based on
the prioritization of the work
and i can remember being at turner
broadcasting on one of my first projects
that i led
for any of our global initiatives we
would have to come all of the leads
would have to come into
a war room everyone's familiar with that
in the technology space
i was in the war room with all the
different leads and people were going
around and introducing themselves
just getting my space set up and i can
remember
a white male we'll call him joe
he introduced himself to me and his role
but when i introduced myself to him i
just introduced myself
and my team he responded by saying to me
oh you must be sitting in for
sam sam
was an amazing white male on my team
that was a true asset
but i was the actual lead and when i
corrected him
he kind of laughed it off and walked
away
it was in that moment that i made the
determination that when i
show up in a technology space that i
will purposely show up
and take up room i will purposely make
sure that i introduce myself to those
that
are known i will make sure that they
understand my role and position within
the technology space
and i will make sure that people
understand the leverage the background
and experience that i have
and you can still do it in a meaningful
way so the way i've navigated is to make
sure that i purposely take up space
and make room for my team to make sure
people have an understanding
that as a woman of color i can lead in
technology
thank you serea that was a really nice
story to share
did anyone have other stories or other
thoughts about this topic that they
wanted to share
that was just so good why spoil it
with more i i do think that that's just
a major theme
that as a woman in technology you might
come
in and have some natural imposter
syndrome
um and then it can get nurtured by just
sort of the things that you run into
the fact that you're alone um but there
are moments where
you're definitely going to have to
intentionally
take up space uh and find support
if you're struggling to do that who can
you
partner with ahead of that meeting so
they help give you space or call on you
if others
aren't um or just the support that you
need behind the scenes when you have
a rough day and you want to ask someone
was that mansplaining or was that
just me being sensitive um and so then
you get
outside perspective and i think that
those things
you know hopefully in the future we
won't have to do them but i think for
now
there are amazing helpful tools to help
you
navigate your career here
thank you alana and just as a follow-up
question
how do you both feel that the gender
landscape may have changed since you
started working in tech i know
some of you have a much longer tenure
than others but have you seen the
landscape change
can i add here just something really
quickly um
one thing that i dealt with was sexual
harassment when i started my career
as the only female in my floor
the only one under 40 at the time under
when i started my career and it was very
difficult it was very difficult and i
know a lot of women
that go through this and it deters them
from
continuing a career in tech i think
things have changed dramatically since
that happened to me because now i think
just in general we have more resources
more more aware
with the metoo movement and everything
that has happened we know that these
stories are real
um so any woman that's out there that's
going through something similar i would
just say
make sure that you reach out um to
someone make sure that you go to your hr
make sure that you have
a partner inside i just know that that
that's one of the toughest things i
would say working
in a male-dominated field
yeah and i would say that i think that
that's a huge
what you're talking about is like i
think if you're if you're looking at the
pure
numbers we still have so far to go
in terms of feeling like we've made
meaningful strides for women and for
other minoritized populations
so it's hard like with numbers like you
know like oh was i like
you know it used to be i was the only
one in the room now there's like three
of us
like i think sometimes it numbers to
feel the huge difference
but if you look in attitudes and
awareness and the dialogue and the
number of training courses we all go to
now
to make us aware of what harassment
looks like
or even microaggressions you know i
think
i think all of that has has changed
a ton um and and it's hard to quantify i
think sometimes
all of those things but i know going
from never talking about it
to having it be a major topic that you
can find multiple trainings a month
about
you can go to author talks about it you
can
um you know work with your employee
resource groups to have
chats where you're really talking
through all of the issues i mean just
the amount
is i could like 100x a thousand x i
can't you know
it's it's always hard to put numbers on
this
but such a big difference from the early
days
yeah and i've really seen a shift in in
leadership commitment and you know
google's starting to share our numbers
externally to really create some
transparency and accountability and from
the numbers perspective we actually have
changed since we started releasing
numbers in 2014 we had
about 20 women in leadership roles about
one in five
and in 2020 we announced we were almost
at 27
so more than um you know one in four of
our leaders now are women so we are
seeing that shift it's slow progress is
not fast enough
as as much as we all want to see but it
is really helpful to see
that leadership awareness and increasing
accountability to really shift
the industry
thank you so much for sharing all of
that you know
it segues me into kind of the next topic
here and i've heard many of you talk
about this already so
while there were so many battles to
fight walls to climb
caverns to cross there's events people's
allies inflection points that really
maybe helped create the opportunity for
us can you speak maybe
in your experiences with respect to your
career in the tech ecosystem
and how and when did you encounter that
experience what did it look like and how
has it
impacted your journey
i i can speak here and say that one of
the things that i did as i took a lean
into
technology in the organization being in
a support role in an operational space
i always wanted to make sure that i
sought out
mentors from a scene leadership level
where i wasn't afraid to
reach out to the director for one-on-one
time or or get time on an
svp's calendar or ceo's calendar for
a product area just so i have that
opportunity to challenge myself
and to learn and to grow so that's one
of the ways that i've navigated even
though
in my vertical i have a sincere passion
of learning and development and will
geek out with anyone all day long i
consistently challenge myself to put
myself
in positions to where i'm attempting to
learn something new
from someone that's been down that road
and then the the other part of that
navigation is then paying it forward
at my level to those that are coming
along the way
that's great and julisa what people or
organizations have helped support your
journey
so for me when i moved to the bay area
being from new york city i really missed
community
so for me building community was the
main my main focus as soon as i got here
um so organizations like shop suite high
tech and ergs were huge for me
i had i learned early on that i had to
build a
almost like board of directors of like
strong women to
guide me through the landscapes of the
things that i was going through that
were new to me
i'm the first in my family to graduate
from college let alone be an engineer
i had no blueprint of what to do
in situations from a corporate
perspective
um so i surrounded myself with
just incredible incredible people
that have really helped me along the way
to the point where
i got at intel um an opportunity
that was created for me for my skill set
um
because of a sponsor spoke for me um and
advocated on my behalf so i i do think
that community building and
you know to serious point uh making sure
that you find people that see things in
you that you might not see for yourself
that's really important that's awesome
let's talk a little bit more about
mentorship and sponsorship
elise do you want to share a little bit
more about your experience with mentors
and sponsors
yeah so i've had luckily some really
great managers that served in
in that role of both mentor and sponsor
as well i know that's not the case
for everyone but particularly one of my
last managers in the marketing
organization really took me under his
wing
helped me build the skills that i needed
to get to the next level helped give me
opportunities to have more visibility
leading high-profile projects allowing
me to come to present to senior
stakeholders
in meetings that i might not normally
have been invited to
helped not only promote me in the
marketing organization but then when i
decided i wanted to make a pivot
into our people work and really helping
support our diversity acquaintance
inclusion
also made connections for me really
helped me explore that
and was willing to even though it was
going to mean he had to find someone new
for his team
knew that it was going to be the right
thing for me overall to be in a role
that i felt more passionate about
and so he was not only supporting that
you know helping me create space on the
side to be networking
and doing some side projects that helped
me validate my desire
to move into that pivot so really being
honest with my manager about what i
wanted what i wanted to
do to go both grow in my level and also
think about my next
move within the company was really
valuable
and outside of normal managers i'd say
also our employee resource groups have
been really valuable we have a huge
women's network and 16 other employee
resource groups so being able to meet
people from different roles and help
build those relationships that can help
you explore what might be next for you
who are those folks that can support you
in your mobility journey
is really a valuable one to be tapping
into those folks that can then
give you advice give you honest feedback
and help advocate and make
opportunities available to you thank you
i was just going to follow up and ask
you know there's probably folks on this
call
that want to learn about how to find a
mentor or how to find a sponsor and i
think you've already
you've already answered that at least
but if anyone has any other suggestions
for women who are looking to find a
mentor or looking to find a sponsor
i'd love for you to share some tips with
our audience today
well i think they're they're pretty
different and sometimes we lump them
together
a mentor is someone you're going to
learn from and and hopefully it's a
win-win relationship where they get a
lot out of talking with you as well
but i think it's it is somewhat
straightforward to think about
people who you want to learn from and i
think sometimes we put a really high bar
on that and think like oh this is
someone i want to marry
but i think that really you can think
about like oh no no you're going on a
nice date
maybe even a speed date and like i have
three questions for you
and i'm gonna write you and say i have
these three questions for you
can i spend a half hour with you and
pick your brain or can we
you know have a virtual coffee right now
maybe one day we'll get back to real
coffees and
i think that that is a really easy low
bar
way to start to form these
relationships these touch points and yes
maybe over time they turn into
a monthly meeting and you build this
long-term mentor relationship but it
might just be that you go to them
because you know they are good at
something
sponsors are somewhat different because
as some people have talked about in some
of their answers
it is someone else seeing something in
you
and because of that they are motivated
to sponsor you to show you things that
maybe you didn't even see
to point out things about um things that
you're good at that you didn't even know
um to talk to you about opportunities
that maybe you wouldn't otherwise hear
about
that i think is a little bit harder to
just go out and be like today i'm gonna
get a sponsor
that's a little bit more about starting
to build
a long-term relationship with people who
are more senior than you
um can you for instance get on your
director's calendar
every so often and start to build that
relationship um
if it's someone just in a totally
different field
but you know that you want to get into
security engineering for
for example can you start to
build that relationship and over time
it's it's them taking you under their
wing
so that one's a little bit less in your
control but building the relationship is
in both cases the key to learning and to
getting advice
and to maybe leading to better things
thank you alana that was a nice
description of explaining the difference
between mentorship and sponsorship
and you're right it takes that little
step to just say
is this person the right fit and
sometimes it's a one-time thing and you
gain so much out of it
or you get mentors that are for multiple
different things in your career so i
really like how you explain that
i think we are now kind of getting to a
point where we could talk a little bit
more
about your career journeys and some of
you have shared that you've moved around
whether it be different industries roles
or throughout the company
so i'd like to talk a little bit more
about what happens when you discover
that there might be a mismatch between
the role you're in
and what you're good at and what you're
inspired to do
and what advice would you give to
someone who's in that position
to pivot and how have you done that
yourself in your career
maybe saria we'll start with you sure
one thing that i always have the analogy
of matriculating through
grade school middle school junior senior
and then whatever undergraduate and
postgraduate
information at every single point you're
always
working to do the next best thing and so
holistically we take that entire thought
process
into our corporate environment into our
professions
and we i can speak for myself i always
assume that
i would always be doing and aspiring to
that next best thing
but i have come up against alignments uh
misalignments in the two decades of
working um
but the one thing i did not grasp in the
beginning
but i do get gather now is even with
any of those misalignments where you
thought that this role was going to be
the absolute best role for you i had to
learn how to take
two or three nuggets of things that i
still learned in that role so
will i navigate to something else will
it be a linear move
instead of a promotion probably because
there's a misalignment here
but i can still have lessons learned
based on the projects that i worked on
based on the team members that i
interacted with based on me selecting
this role
and looking for another role and looking
at things to actually look at
when i'm talking to a hiring manager or
or meeting with team members
so i the one thing that i would like for
everyone to take away from this is
sometimes it's not a move for promotion
when you have misalignments
you could have lateral moves and you
still need to take the things that you
learned
from that situation to become a better a
better employee a better professional
and a better human being
thank you serea can i add to that just a
little bit
um you just reminded me of something
really powerful that i've read
that it's called destination addiction
when is that we
are so focused on what the next thing is
that we
forget to respect the opportunity which
is one of the things that i love about
the three respects and respecting the
opportunity sometimes means that did i
give this opportunity did i squeeze all
the juice out of this opportunity
before i'm already thinking oh i want
this next thing that i want this next
other um outcome so thank you for that
syria
yeah i would just add and this isn't
meant to be a devil's advocate or
anything it's actually to add on to that
is that i think what i like about all of
this is is
the idea of being deliberate because i
think sometimes
when we feel like we're in a bad
situation our instinct is to flee
and that's pretty natural um but i think
sometimes in fleeing you don't make the
smartest decisions right like you just
grab what you can and you run
and you might run to the wrong place you
might not
respect the opportunity and take what
you could from it
at the same time i also see that
sometimes we stay too long
we keep trying we think it's us
and so what i what i really am
counseling people to
do is be deliberate you know figure out
what's going on
see whether there's a couple things that
you want to try
before you move on to make things
go better to maybe it's the culture that
you feel misaligned with and you feel
like there are things that you can try
there
maybe there's some things that you want
to do before you move on because you're
a manager whatever it is
be deliberate do those things
but then set a timeline send to set a
deadline for yourself
and if you're not feeling better if it
is not better if it is still misaligned
then very deliberately decide
what you're going to next what you're
going to do next
um so that you don't get to this place
where you feel
powerless and like you can't take the
next steps that you need
to um and that your career isn't in your
hands that's great
thank you alana so what types of tools
or resources would you recommend to our
audience
to help find the right role for them are
there specific tools or resources that
you yourselves have used or that you
would recommend
as they're going through this journey
the silence may be because there's no
magic here right
um i think i think a lot of us are just
using
whatever we can when we can find it i'll
throw out one and then maybe each of us
can throw out one um
i found it helpful to
think about my job search as a job port
like
almost like how you applied to schools
maybe if you applied to colleges where
you had
safe schools reach schools and dream
schools
but i found it really helpful to
think of my opportunities there and pick
some safe roles like you know that just
might be posted
that you feel like you meet all the job
criteria for
but also pick some ones that seem out of
reach
and explore them um and so that can just
be off of the job boards or it be it can
be because you heard about them
separately
but i think i found it as a tool really
nice so i don't
over in like i push myself to reach for
things
but i also there's a piece of me
okay everybody's barking and ringing um
anyway there's a piece of me that wants
to feel really safe and so
it yeah anyway you get the point
go on without man i think i think i
wanna brings up a really good point the
one thing that i've tapped into
in many instances across along my career
is my network and so a lot of times
you're in a role or that may be
like a mismatch or misposition for you
but
it seems to come a little bit clearer
when you talk to people in other areas
of your business that
oh wait a minute they're facing the same
challenges the same problems
because you know there could be a
strategy misalignment within the
organization itself um but
my network has been a an abundance of of
help
and and helping me navigate yeah i was
going to say plus
i'll go ahead go ahead okay i'll just
quickly build on that i was going to say
relationship building as well both to
get perspective
about what might be available and next
for me as well as actually unlocking
opportunities um you know folks that i
reached out to or did a project with or
had networked with um you know later
became opportunities to move into the
team full time
so really thinking of rebranding
networking if it sounds scary it's just
authentic relationship building right
how do i get to know somebody
understand their role understand their
team and their needs
in ways that might end up opening
something up for me later on
what i was gonna say was um i think it
depends on where you are
in your career journey right because
i've had uh instances when i had to look
at what my values are
and let's say i was in a psychologically
unsafe situation
my values are to find psychological
safety
find a manager that believes in me
and um or get parity on
you know whatever getting paid all of
these different things depending on
where you're at
and what your struggles are i think that
those
things become like more valuable than
others so
that would be my advice is just to do a
value landscape situation where you
understand
what is up most important for you at
that time
that's great so i'm gonna pivot the
conversation a bit here
so i understand some of you are moms so
can you tell me a little bit about what
it was like to transition your lifestyle
as a mom working in tech and
what advice would you give either
current moms or future moms to be
and let's start with jaleesa
so i'm not a mom but i am an expecting
mom i'm expecting a baby
in eight weeks and he's just kicking
right now
he's like yeah yeah um
what i will share is that this has been
a very
transformational journey i'm not even
there yet
um just the things that i'm having to
take into consideration
as of right now and i also want to
acknowledge my privilege and the fact
that because of the pandemic and because
i've been able to work from home
i've been like you know what is it
called nausea
nauseous and been able to do it at home
and turn off my camera where a lot of
women aren't afforded these
opportunities
you know i'm joining these mom groups
where women are saying oh i only get six
weeks of maternity leave and here at
google we're so fortunate
so just learning all these things
because of the experience that i'm going
through has
put like a different perspective first
of all if you're a mom like
power on i will never take my mom for
granted not that i ever did but that
i will never take her french ever again
that's all i want to share
janine this is a topic that i could talk
about all day
because i love being a mother um
it has been a challenge but i will i
always identify
myself as this professional that could
just do it all
and then i became a mother and i had to
go through like this full
transformation because that over
everything is my number one priority and
main job
um the two things that have helped me
pivot as a mother
working in corporate america they still
wanted to be that leader i still wanted
to
do all things uh technology was
one having a sound support system
and two like setting boundaries related
to my family and what that time looks
like
like on the the support system side i
cannot
tell everyone how many opportunities
that i've turned down
just because i have to be in a space
where my
my village is where my family is my
mothers my fathers
so that i have the opportunity to travel
40 50
of the time in order to complete my job
um
and then around setting boundaries it's
like
being in control and having in input
into
like when something as simple as a
conference
or a networking event or things that
take you away from the home
i'm always at the front of the table
looking at the baseball schedule the
recital schedule
and saying how can i pivot these things
and it's
it's not an easy plight
but you know i've taken several red-eye
flights
to make sure that i can see my son hit
the home run or
make it to that parent teachers
conference but it hasn't been perfect
all the time like sometimes i get the
tablet up at the game so i can see
but i i do make it a point to
keep my support system intact and and
clearly set boundaries so that i have
that balance
but it's all worth it it's all
absolutely worth it
i hope so i'm scared well i'll just
piggyback on that
and and and just because you made me
think of something that i'll often say
which is like
if someone asked me like what do i think
about this having it all concept
i'll say well like are we talking about
over
a lifetime i think that that sometimes
we try to have it all
now and what happens when you're a mom
is
you will literally see the hours of the
day run out
it'll be like 10 30 p.m and you'll be
like
should i shower now like will i have
time
in the morning like how is this gonna
work
um and that's like for a shower let
alone like
yoga like self-care like all of the
fancy words we throw out nowadays
um and so while i love it in some
respects because it's led me to like
true prioritization like i do not have
time for us to get out of this meeting
without some clear action items because
this has got to make progress
like this is it this is the meeting um i
think it's also been
a little bit about deciding like okay i
don't need to do it
all right now like this year beca
pandemic i've got to spend more time
helping my 12 year old
through school um and it means like i'm
definitely not going to be able to
do some of the side activities i like to
do both at work and
outside um or i take on less of it
in order to make that pivot but next
year
you know maybe it'll be different right
so you you can
kind of pivot and have some goals and
know
and know that careers are long right
like nowadays
most of us are gonna work multiple
decades right
and so thinking about like okay well
maybe these two years
i'm gonna focus on like getting back to
a normal sleep schedule
and then i'll make that big career pivot
um i think that that sometimes helps
especially with our own feelings of like
pressure we put on ourselves
it's not that you're saying never it
just might not be
this six months um right now
that's great thank you all so much for
sharing that angelisa congratulations
we'd love to hear more how your journey
goes as a mom and tech
um i'd love to now just talk a little
bit about
some of you that have moved from an ic
what we call an individual contributor
role to a people manager role
um could you share a little bit about
how that transition was for you
and maybe a little bit about that
journey how you made that transition
from your first ic role to
being a people manager for the first
time
oh badly i feel like i'm always
interjecting when they're silenced but
like i'll just i'll just
it was it was hard i was really really
good at being
an individual contributor and i
thought maybe for the first six months i
was hitting out of the ballpark with
management
and then i started to get feedback about
how
i just really wasn't a great manager
like i wasn't
i wasn't taking time to foster people
and coach them and help them through
their journey
i was still treating it like like
like a check box on my list which i'd
always been very good at
and so i do think that that
we shouldn't be too hard on ourselves
it's a real journey to do but i also
think like
we should knowingly like if you just
sort of
get plopped into management i think
sometimes we might not
sort of internalize that and knowingly
start to shift away
from all of our ic projects to spending
more time
with our people understanding what their
challenges are what their career goals
are etc
and so this can kind of sneak up on us
and we can get maybe some of this
feedback at first
so i guess my main tip is if you can go
into it knowingly
get some advice from people who've done
this before
and and spend some time with your people
listening to them
and do it with a lot more intention
i think that that's the best way to do
it now that said
just listen to the feedback later you
know i think sometimes
our first instinct too might be to push
away the feedback so
if you start to get the feedback as you
are going through that transition
just know that that's actually pretty
normal and it probably means there's
something
a little off in your in your ic balance
i wrote a whole series of articles on
linkedin about how i did this terribly
um and how i got performance feedback
over the years so
feel free if you want to know more um to
see my huge maya culpa to my
my poor early guinea pigs at google
elana elon is so spot on i can say like
as an individual contributor type a
personality is like
the dead the devil is in the details and
i had to know like
every single thing happening going on
launching
the article meeting and i totally
bummed over a decade ago with this
but over time you go through this
journey of having a better understanding
of
um making sure that you have the best
talent in place
and then trust that talent to execute
effectively
and that allows you to lift yourself up
over
your business or your team and providing
the strike the
straight strategy and guidance and then
over time
they're one of two managers or leaders
that you can become whether it be
operational or people
and i definitely lean into the people
management space because
i love developing careers i love
removing roadblocks
um but i think that was more because i
got the feedback that i was being
too into the wheeze on the operational
side
so that's where my where my power where
my powers lie
were the people management space
thank you so much for sharing all of
that i do want to really differentiate
here the difference between being an
actual people manager or a manager
versus a leader and as you all know
you're not required to manage people to
be a leader at the company
so can some of you share a little bit
more about how women can step
into a leadership role or advance
into being a leader in the company and
maybe elise will start with you
yeah so definitely i agree with that
philosophy that everyone is a leader
in their own right whether or not you're
managing folks and the things that i
think about when i think about
leadership and stepping into those roles
are
really starting with self-awareness
understanding your strengths your skill
set
and your values and then really building
vision
you know where do you want to go what do
you want to be stepping into what sort
of impact do you want to make and then
advocating for yourself and really
sharing that you know making that known
to your manager to the people around you
of what sort of impact you want to have
where you want to be going so that you
can start to build out those sponsor
relationships and people can really
advocate for you open up stretch
opportunities think about you know what
is the next high visibility project that
i want to raise my hand for
and being aware of where imposter
syndrome or
you know confidence might be holding you
back saying i'm not quite ready yet or
i'm afraid and really going out there
right giving yourself that boost of
confidence having the support system in
place to say people have my back people
fail
all the time and we learn from that we
grow from that and really putting
yourself out there because we need more
women in leadership we need more women
in leadership and technology
and every single one of you has so much
to offer and add to this world and
whatever space that you're in right now
so it's like
go for it self-awareness vision advocacy
and stretch yourself
that was perfect thank you so much elite
so we're running short on time here i
can't believe this panel kind of flew by
before we knew it so
i'm just gonna end with a couple last
questions and i'd love for each of you
to kind of take the time um in finishing
out this panel
um either what is your biggest piece of
advice for women that want to work in
tech
and as well as what tactical steps and
actions do you want to see in changing
the narrative for women in tech and you
can answer both questions or one of them
but
just ending kind of your thoughts on
this panel with our audience here today
and anyone can start
i guess i can start one of the things
i'll answer the latter janine
i really technology companies develop
some of the most diverse
products and services for a very diverse
world
although when we sit in the conference
rooms or on video conferences you don't
see that diversity
so i'm very very much of an advocate
around diversity equity inclusion in
this space
um and creating the idea that
women of color women of different
ethnicities
can do just as well in the technology
space
and so that's that's why i'm leaning in
around what things can be changed
more diversity and i can go second
i think with that um i'd like to say
that i wish more women would consider
technology because we need your voice um
to shape our products
to be able to do better out there and
the quote that um i also want to say
is even when your voice shakes speak
because i've had many situations where i
felt really scared but i still said
something and it was impactful
to tell my women out there speak
i'll share i'd say for for women lift as
you climb as you grow
and advance in your career let's be
locking arms with others and thinking
who else we can pull up with us
to really support this growing ecosystem
and
for companies we really need to be
taking seriously with
clear goals that are ambitious
transparency
measuring progress and moving the needle
forward
this is not about a problem with women
or women needing to be fixed or
developed more
this is about an industry opening up
doors that have previously been closed
to women and people of color
and truly taking that seriously so i'm
excited about the direction we have to
go ahead
and i would just add that i would love
to see us shift the stories that we
share
um often we tell stories about women who
made it to the tippy top
or very technical women and i think
we've just got
so many different roles so many
different backgrounds
so many different people who are
thriving in tech and
i just want to see us make sure to tell
the stories across so that
if you're in high school and trying to
decide could you belong in tech
you would see examples you would hear
those stories
um that would inspire you because there
are so many women not just on this call
but outside of this call
to be inspired by and if you're one of
those women
my advice to you is just ask um
because i wish there's so many times and
and
none that i think like were crazy and
ruined my career but
so many moments where i didn't realize
that i could
ask for something that i could ask for
what i wanted
ask for what i needed and i think we are
still raising awareness and if people
aren't mind readers if they don't know
you're interested in that job
if they don't know you're thinking about
growth that way
they just don't know and so just ask
that's my advice amazing thank you
so much to all of our panelists for your
time let's give them a virtual round of
applause
so thank you to elena elise jalisa and
saria
and thank you so much for letting me
moderate your panel it was an honor
i hope all of you that tuned in had the
motivation and the courage to create
which is our theme
for this conference and i thank you all
for your time
thank you
[Music]
[Applause]
next up you can stay on this track
for lauren hassan who will share steps
you can take to start building
your value and put your tech education
to work for you
or switch to the second track for a
session on
hands-on learning with google cloud and
many more
[Music]
happy international women's day i am so
excited to be here with you celebrating
with
tens of thousands of women in tech from
across the globe
and i gotta tell you i am absolutely
pinching myself
that i that i've been asked to share my
story to speak with all of you it is
such an honor to be here but
i'm pinching myself because if you had
told me
nine years ago that i'd be here today
speaking to all of you
i would not have believed you because
nine years ago
i was at the absolute end of my rope
i had just been laid off from one of the
worst
dead end jobs that i had ever had
and i was absolutely
defeated absolutely defeated have you
ever been there you're just
absolutely defeated because that was me
to make matters worse i had zero
marketable tech skills
i had zero network
and i had zero job prospects
and even worse i had zero money in my
bank account
my credit cards were almost maxed out
and i was relying on
tiny unemployment checks just to make
ends meet
it was a bad bad situation
and i was absolutely terrified at the
time
i was terrified i'd never find someone
to hire me
and give me a shot and i was terrified
it
that i'd never be able to take care of
myself again
and when i wasn't pounding the pavement
looking for a lifetime
any job any job to pay the bills
i was on my couch ugly crying have you
ever been there
ugly crying that was me it was not
a pretty situation so
i took whatever money i had left on my
credit cards
and i threw myself a hail mary
and i hired myself a career coach
because i was stuck
and i knew i needed help to get unstuck
and i needed an
outside perspective to help me figure
out what to do next
and she had me take a career assessment
to figure out what i should be doing
and the results of the career assessment
completely
surprised me they overwhelmingly said i
should be developing
software and you see that came was a
complete shock to me because
i thought that door had already closed
you see i
have an undergraduate degree in computer
science
but after some less than stellar college
internships i
completely left tech behind
and gone a completely different
direction i
am an attrition number right out of
school
and here i was being told that i should
be developing software and
put my degree to work and you may think
this is great news i
had the computer science degree but but
my
tech skills were over seven
years outdated which is like an eternity
intact my skills were archaic
i was our kick and
to put this in perspective when i
graduated
not only did the iphone not exist
the razer didn't even exist and sms
text messaging wasn't even a thing yet
that's how outdated my tech skills were
and i remember thinking how in the world
am i ever
gonna relearn my tech skills and get
back into tech
much less convince someone to hire me
but i also knew it was my best
chance it was my only hope
and so i took action i took action and i
enrolled myself in an
evening community college course to
slowly
relearn my tech skills and while i was
relearning my tech skills and studying
at night
i was pounding the pavement during the
day cold calling
every company an agency and tech company
i could find
looking to get my foot just get it in
the door
i gotta tell you this was hard this was
grueling i got
turned down and flat out ghosted more
times than i can count in fact
i only got one yes
and it wasn't even that great of a yes
it was for an internship
level role internship level role to come
in
teach myself ios and i only had
90 days to prove myself to
convince them to keep me on and now
i was even more terrified i was
terrified i would come it in
come in lay it all on the line give it
everything i had and then that wouldn't
be enough
and then not only would i be back at
square one but i'd be even worse off
and even more defeated
but i also knew if i didn't put myself
out there
if i didn't give myself the chance to
succeed
i would likely always be wondering
what if
so i took that leap of faith i put
myself
out there and in less than two
years i not only managed to survive that
90-day trial period
and keep that job but i had managed to
absolutely thrive
i've been one of a handful of ios
developers
worldwide who'd worked on some of the
first
ipad apps for major television networks
to bring
tv shows and tv movies to your ipad
which was
brand new technology nine years ago
i played a leadership role in getting
content on your
your tv to sync in real time with
content on your ipad for a major
television
network's 25th anniversary special
which was groundbreaking bleeding edge
technology we were the first
developers to be doing this at the time
and i
had reached top of field for ios
developers i had reached ios mecca
my app was one of only 27 apps that was
featured in apple's ios 7
groundbreaking keynote as a launch
partner and that's my app
my app next to facebook and twitter and
paypal
and with everything that i was doing my
hard work had
not gone unnoticed i had won the
company-wide award
not once not twice but four
times at this international agency in
just two
years and i wasn't just hitting it out
of the park at work i was also
really active in the tech community and
in the hackathon community and i had
been invited to and i had won
a number of really high profile
hackathons
including winning the international
south by hackathon
two years in a row
and then i got the invitation of a
lifetime
i was one of a hundred tech innovators
worldwide
they invited the likes of craig newmark
the founder of craigslist k
koplovs the founder of usa television
networks and then me
to fly on a private 747 jet
from san francisco to london to attend
the ukj
innovation conference to present ideas
to the united
nations and with everything that i had
done
at the company everything that i was
doing in the community my company's
executive leadership had
taken notice and they came to me
and they asked me to have the company's
innovation and culture committee
and it wasn't just my own company's
executive leadership that had taken
notice i was
regularly getting recruited by top tech
companies
google apple facebook were regularly
calling me trying to woo me away from my
company to come work for them
in just two years i had gone from
absolute
rock bottom zero absolutely zero
zero marketable tech skills zero network
zero job prospects zero money in my bank
account to a
top highly recruited woman in tech
with awards behind her name and i had
nearly quintupled
my salary and now today
i am living out how i define success
by day i work remotely from my home in
dallas for
a silicon valley payments company where
i am
one of the most senior engineers and i'm
the architect of our entire voice
payment system
and all of our messaging capabilities
and i've owned
all of application security for a
payments company where
application security really matters
and i'm also the founder of the
developer platform i help women in tech
just like you get ahead stand out
and earn more in their careers
and what i learned through all of this
is that
it's not some quantum leap that's gonna
help you get ahead someone's not gonna
come along and tap you on the shoulder
and make some giant leap
instead it's the small actions taken
consistently and repeatedly that
compound over time
and yield incredible results that help
you get ahead to stand out
and really transform your career
and that's what i'm going to share with
you today i'm going to share with you
the five
simple things that i did consistently
and repeatedly
in my own career to get ahead to stand
out and to earn more so that
you too can leave today with immediate
actions that you can take to build your
own best career to get ahead to stand
out
and finally earn what you're worth now
first and foremost
the conversation starts today but it
does not end
and i want each and every one of you to
be connected with me connect with me on
linkedin
follow me on twitter the conversation
starts today but let's stay connected
because we're all women intact together
and the second thing is this is a social
friendly presentation be taking pictures
sharing out what resonates with you
in the bottom left hand corner of every
slide are
are my handles and hashtags for the
event share out with the world what
you're doing what you're learning
and tell them what you're taking away
from today's presentation
now the first and most important thing
that i did
to get ahead to transform my career
is i took action i took action
over and over again
and when i say i took action i mean i
stepped up i showed up and i asked even
when it terrified me and
even when i doubted myself
i took action one of the
highlights of my career was when i was
invited to attend the ukg
innovation conference i mean i'm
pinching myself to this day
that i still got this incredible
invitation to go and present to the
united nations
but the the most incredible part of this
opportunity to me
is that anyone i worked with at the time
honestly they were more qualified and
talented than me could have also had
this incredible invite
but they didn't step up show up and ask
over
and over again like i did and that's why
i got the invite
you see i can trace this incredible
invitation back to just
two months into that new engineering job
i had
and the head of engineering pulled our
entire department aside
and asked all of us to volunteer an
entire saturday
yeah volunteer an entire saturday
to mentor at a local hackathon
as you might guess only a couple of us
volunteered and said
we would step up and do it and i was one
of them
and i still remember to this day sitting
outside the innovation center
before 8 a.m on a saturday morning
in my car silently praying to myself
that i didn't make a fool of myself
i was that nervous
but i stepped out despite my fear i went
in
and i discovered yeah there there were a
lot of people who knew knew more than me
but i found the small areas where i did
know knowledge
and where i could contribute and that's
where i added value
and while i was there i made it a point
to meet the organizer
and the organizer invited me and all of
my fellow mentors to continue to attend
his events
but only i showed up and i didn't just
show up once
i showed up over and over again
so when the same organizer announced
several months later that he was hosting
a high profile hackathon
at the international south by conference
in austin
and to even get your foot in the door to
this hackathon you had to have one of
the events
1500 conference tickets which
i guarantee you i did not have at the
time
i took action i called up the the
conference
organizer the the event organizer and i
pitched
myself to him as a right-hand volunteer
and i ended up not only getting my foot
in the door to the event
i got to work at the door of the event
where i got to meet every single
high-profile and important person who
was attending
then something happened literally
overnight on the first day
one of the hackathon teams needed an
additional team member an
engineer at 11 p.m that night
i went from volunteer to engineer
because i was an
engineer and we ended up winning at that
hackathon
so when one year later the same
organizer announced he was hosting an
even higher profile hackathon this time
in tandem with american airlines which
was promoting their
international high profile re-brand of
the company
and this time the event was invite only
i got an invite i not only got an invite
i got to bring
my very own team to the event
and while we were there we met a guy
from american airlines he wasn't part of
the hackathon
and he followed up with us after we we'd
wanted the hackathon
but only i replied to his email
and i didn't just reply to his email i
cultivated that relationship so when a
couple months later
british airways announced they were
hosting an innovation
hackathon in the sky event that was
invite only for
top innovators worldwide i mean a who's
who list of people in tech
and american airlines got to invite five
people i got one of those invites
i'll tell you i didn't do anything
special other than step up show up and
ask
over and over again and it led to an
incredible invite
and it's something that you can do to
starting
today now the second thing i did to
really get ahead
to build my value and cement myself as a
valuable asset
was i built my network before i needed
it
and i did this because i had learned a
painful lesson early in my career that
it's not enough to
do good work to get ahead but people who
influence your career they need to know
you
and they need to know the work the good
work that you do in order to advance
your career
and i was fortunate enough to learn this
lesson just
one year out of college and at the time
i wasn't even in tech i was an
investment banker and investment banks
have every every all their employees in
analyst class
and at the end of the year they take all
the analysts and they rank them
into um into tiers for the analyst class
and the tier that you're ranked in out
of five determines your year-end bonus
and the the tiers have a difference of
tens of thousands of dollars so
the two you're ranked in really matters
and i went into my performance review
and i heard nothing but great things
but i was ranked in the second to talk
tear
and so i asked a question that changed
my life forever i asked him well
what held me back and they said lauren
you're great at what you do you're in a
branch office here in silicon valley
valley and everyone here in the office
knows you and the work that you do
but not enough people in our new york
city headquarters who have influence
over your career know you
and know the great work that you do
right then and there i learned one of
the most powerful lessons in my career
i learned that it's not enough to do
great work to get ahead but people who
influence your career people have power
over your career they need to know you
and they need to know the work that you
do
so day one getting back into tech
i made it my goal my priority to
build my network before i needed it
i started by building my internal
network i made it my goal to meet
everyone at the company
that i could possibly meet and get to
know them i joined committees to meet
people across disciplines and across
different
job levels i went to meetups i went to
happy hours i went to breakfast i even
went so far as to join
the new hire welcome committee that way
i could meet everyone
as they walked in the front door and it
paid off within a year not only did i
know
everyone at the company but everyone in
the company knew me
and they knew the work that i did and
when when someone i worked with had
something they needed solved cross
company they came to me because they
knew
that i knew the people to help them
solve their problems
and it wasn't just my colleagues who
were coming to me to help them solve
their problems it was executive
leadership too
when they had some important initiative
they needed to roll out and get buy-in
across the company they came to me
because they knew i had the network and
they knew i had the influence to help
them roll out their most important
initiatives when you have the network
when you have the influence
to solve problems for other people you
immediately become an asset and you
become more valuable to your network and
in your own
career but i wasn't just building my
internal network
at the same time i was also building my
external network
and i was going to every conference
every meetup
hackathons uh you name it if there
wasn't an external event out in the
community
i was finding a way to attend that and i
gotta tell you this was this was
actually really hard and a stretch for
me because
i'm an introvert you may not guess it
because i'm speaking here today but i
am so naturally shy so this was
something that was
completely out of my comfort zone
but i got it done and here here's how i
did it i made myself
micro commitments i didn't try to build
an entire big network overnight he said
i took it one small step
one stall small micro commitment at a
time
and i'd start by making three small
micro commitments to myself that i
that i couldn't not do they were so
small i said lauren
pick an event pick one event and commit
to showing up to the event
then while you're there you don't even
have to stay the whole time you just
have to stay long enough to meet
three people three new people
i'd meet those three people sometimes
i'd stay longer but a lot of times i'd
hightail it out and then i had to
promise myself to show up one more
time and i did this over and over again
and i built my confidence and every time
i got more and more confident
and i'd start by meeting some new people
and then i started recognizing people
that i had met before at events and then
something else happened people started
recognizing
me and coming up to me and what i
discovered is i wasn't the only person
who was nervous that i'd be standing by
myself in a corner
other people were just as nervous and
when they recognized me they would come
up
to me and then it got to a point where i
couldn't even walk
in the front door of an event without
someone recognizing me
and coming up to talk to me and now
i not only have an amazing local network
but i have an incredible
global network and i'll be the first to
tell you that i am not the fastest
i'm not the fanciest i'm not the most
talented software engineer
but i am one of the most networked and
when someone in my network has a problem
they come to me because i am
top of mind because they know me and
they know the work that i do and they
know that if i can't immediately
solve their problem i can get them to
connected to someone who can
when you become the person in your
network who solves other people's
problem
you immediately become an asset and you
become incredibly valuable to your
company
and to your internal and external
network as well
now the third thing that i did to
exponentially grow
my value was i was constantly learning
new and valuable skills and i was
building my portfolio to show that i had
those skills
and i was doing this because i learned
one of the fastest ways to accelerate
my career growth was to figure out what
skills
every company valued and really wanted
to hire for
and where that overlapped with where
there wasn't a lot of talent in the
marketplace that had those skill sets
i would find where they intersect i'd go
learn those new skills and then i'd show
that i had those skills
and nine years ago i learned ios
ios was brand new technology at the time
every company was looking to hire an ios
developer
and not a lot of people had those skill
sets they only had a couple years and
there weren't
of experience and there weren't a lot of
people with these skill sets
and the operative words here are taught
myself
i didn't wait for someone to tap me on
the shoulder and show me the ropes
and come up and teach me how to do ios i
went out
and i got the experience for myself
i read books i did video tutorials
i picked up bugs that no one wanted to
work on i volunteered for
projects that no one wanted to touch
with the 10 foot pole because
i was eager to put my new skills to work
and
show people what i could do and i got to
be honest at first
these opportunities did not come to me
they did not just easily present
themselves
but i did not let that stop me when
opportunities did not come for me
i went out and i created the
opportunities for myself and for me
i did this through hackathons there are
a number of other ways that you can also
do this for yourself but
but for me i one of the most powerful
ways that i use was hackathons
and i did that because it killed
multiple birds with one stone
they were time bound they had a
something to
show in my portfolio at the end of it i
met new people
and it was expected that you were
testing out new skills
so it filled checked a lot of the boxes
for me
and what i did is i used every bug i
used every hackathon every
new project to level up to get to a next
level
to to get to a bigger project and it
paid off that's how i ended up featured
in
apple's ios keynote working on some of
the biggest
projects out there at the time
and nine years ago i started by learning
ios
and i invested in learning these new and
valuable skills but
this is something that i continue to do
to this day in fact three four years ago
i looked around and i said it's time to
level up again
i was top of field and i said it's time
to level up again
and find new and valuable skills that
make me marketable
that make me a linchpin that make me
really valuable and stand out from the
crowd
and for me i retooled not once but twice
i re-tooled into security
and i retooled into voice and back end
and i gotta tell you
it was hard it was hard to start over
and learn a new skill set
and not be good at something especially
when you were top of field
but it was absolutely
worth it because i invested in learning
new invaluable skills emerging skill
sets
i not only became incredibly valuable to
my company and filled a direct
hurting need that they had at the time
and filled a hole that they had
but i became incredibly valuable and
marketable
as a woman in tech in the marketplace i
am constantly
receiving incredibly lucrative offers
because i have such a
unique skill set and valuable skill set
now the good news for you is that you
don't just have to get into security
there are a
number of different opportunities for
you to also get ahead
and my advice to you is this don't pick
a technology that people can have
20 years of experience in that that it's
been around for a long
time instead figure out where i what i
call
is the quote front of the line figure
out new technologies that haven't been
around very long that lots of employers
are interested in hiring people for
that not a lot of people have those
skill set learn those skills and then
you essentially
jump to the front of the line you can
bypass people who have years of
experience because you're learning the
new and valuable skill sets
you don't have to have 10 years of
experience you have to have
just experience to show that you can do
it
and when you jump to the front of the
line do one more thing
and that's keep what i call an atta girl
journal
and i'll give you information later in
this presentation how you can get your
own hands on a free
developer at a girl journal and what i
do is this is something that i use
personally for myself
to do two things number one i track
everything that i've worked on
what i've done the accomplishments what
went into it
how i was feeling at the time was this
hard for me did it feel like a stretch a
challenge that i have overwhelming
feelings of imposter syndrome
i use it to be able to to update my
resume to talk about myself in
interviews
i use it to update linkedin and and i
also
use it to reflect on my progress i'll
come back
quarterly and annually and review what
i've done
and what i'll see is over time i've
forgotten how much i've grown and things
that were once challenging for me are
now
natural and easy to do and that's called
growth
and that helps me build my confidence
and so
often times we as women in tech are too
hard on ourselves
and don't give ourselves credit for how
far we've come
and so i'll use that to build my
confidence to strengthen that confidence
muscle
and i'll also use it to do one more
thing
and that's communicate my value and talk
about the value that i provide through
what i've done
and i learned that the powerful lesson
that it's not enough to do good work to
get ahead this is
not something you leave to chance you
cannot do good work in a silo
and expect someone to come around and
take notice and tap you on the shoulder
and pull you up you cannot do that you
have to be your
own best advocate to get ahead
and to stand out and for me
i had to become my own best advocate and
i and i
at first i thought it was going to take
being icky and self-promotional which
didn't feel natural to me
so i found a way that that's really
authentic and genuine to me and it's
really simple
and it's something that i bet you're
already doing that you can put to power
as well and what i do is when i would
finish a project
uh at work or if i went to a hackathon
or if i went to conference even if i
read a new book if i learned something
new i would take lots of pictures
i would take pictures with the people
that i met things that i
worked on interesting sessions that i
attended just like me be attending
sessions at this event
i had take a lot of pictures then at the
end
i would select one picture and i would
post it
with a simple tagline with the right
hashtags and handles and
tag the right people and i would post it
not in one
but in two places the first place i
would post it would be to my external
network
for me that's posting to linkedin and
maybe twitter and facebook
because i want my external network to
know about the work that i'm doing
i want my external network to see what
i'm up to but i'm learning what i'm
involved with
the second place you might not have
thought about those equally as important
for you to post to
is my internal network i post for me
it's on my company slack it might be
a microsoft product for you whatever
your company uses to communicate
out what people are doing internally i
would post to the internal
to the internal message board in fact
posting a simple picture with the
caption
at my current company is to our internal
slack is exactly how i got my foot in
the door
in security and got a new valuable skill
set
but there's no magic in one single post
one
single post to to linkedin or twitter or
slack
is not gonna change your life the magic
kicks in
when you do it over and over again when
your network when your
your your colleagues when your external
network see you
involved in the same types of projects
the same types of events
contributing to the same types of
thought leadership when they see that
over and over again something
magical happens you build yourself
a reputation and i didn't just build
myself a reputation
one reputation i built myself multiple
reputations and i'm continuing to build
those reputations
to this day at first i built myself a
reputation
for as an expert in ios then i built
myself a reputation as someone who
competes in and wins
high profile hackathons then i built
myself a reputation
as someone who's really active in the
the tech community
and then as an i uh as a security and
woman and security expert
then as a speaker then as an expert in
voice
and now as a speaker and advocate for
women in tech i'm still
building reputations to this day
and it doesn't take being icky and
self-promotional i've done it in a way
that's authentic
and it's genuine to me and i post no
more on average than
once a week at the most and when i first
started out i was only posting once a
month
it's something incredibly simple that
you can do you're likely already doing
and the power kicks in when you do it
over
and over again
now the last and most
powerful thing that i did to transform
my career was i invested in myself
i invested in myself i
invested in my career and i invested in
my future and my family's future
and i invested in myself because i see
and view myself
as an asset something that if i invest
in i can grow
my value and yield dividends
and i my first investment was investing
in a career coach because
i was stuck not only was stuck but i
knew i needed an
outside perspective to help come in and
get me unstuck
and that's what she did she helped me
get clarity on what i should be doing
next
and she helped me accelerate my pro my
progress to getting back into tech
my only regret is that i didn't do this
sooner i maxed out
credit cards to make this happen it
terrified me
but my only regret in hindsight is that
i did not
invest in myself sooner
my second investment was enrolling
myself in an evening community college
course
this may seem like a small investment to
relearn my tech skills at night
but it paid off big time because when i
was interviewing at tech companies
i wasn't just talking about getting back
into tech
i was actually backing it up with my
time and money and i was
actually doing it and when i got my foot
in the door
i didn't stop there in fact i doubled
down and i invested myself
even more if there was a book or
training video that i needed to advance
my career and
up level and my company didn't get it
for me i went out and i got it for
myself
if there was an event an industry event
i needed to attend to sharpen my skills
or build my network
i found a way to get my foot in the door
if there was a mentor that i needed to
to help me get to the next level i
didn't wait for someone to come
alongside me and tap me on the shoulder
i went out and i hired those coaches for
myself to get to the next level
and because i invested in myself people
who are once my mentors are now coming
to me today
for advice the tables have completely
turned and this isn't something that i
did
to just accelerate my career to getting
back into tech
this is something that i have continued
to do
all along for the last nine years and
it's something i continue to do and to
prioritize
to this day i
invest in multiple professional coaches
because i know the value of having
someone who's achieved what i want to
achieve
come alongside me show me the ropes
short circuit the learning process and
give me
outside perspective i am a member of
multiple membership communities
because i know the value of being
surrounded with like-minded individuals
who have the same aspirations
who are on the same journey have similar
goals
i regularly attend industry events to to
sharpen my skills to up level to
learn new things and to meet other
people
and then i'm going to share something
that a lot of people might not talk
about but i think is
absolutely critical i invest in
professional counseling because i know
that if i don't take care of myself
and my mental health first
i cannot even begin to think about
taking care of my career
you may be looking at this and being
like lauren this
is a lot and i'll tell you it is i've
invested thousands of dollars in myself
not all at once but over the course of
nine years i've invested a lot in myself
and i'll tell you to this day every
single time i make an investment in
myself i have a
moment where i catch my breath because
it scares me
but my biggest regret is what my life
would look like if i
didn't invest in myself
i see myself as an investment and i look
back
and it terrifies me to think what my
life would look like if i had not
invested in myself because i stepped out
despite my fear
invested in myself i went from absolute
rock bottom
nine years ago zero marketable tech
skills
zero job prospects zero network
and zero in my bank account
to a top highly recruited
award-winning woman in tech with global
connect connections and i have more than
quinn
toppled my base salary
if that is not a return on investment
i don't know what is
now i've shared some incredibly personal
stories with you today i've shared what
it was like to to be at rock bottom
ugly crying on my couch and i've really
peeled back that curtain and i've let
you
have an inside look on what it really
took behind the scenes to
to to build my career and transform it
in such a short amount of time
and i did that to to to inspire you not
to impress you but to inspire you and
show you what's possible
but i know there are a few of you out
there who are going lauren it's great
that you can do it but
can i really do it too and i gotta tell
you i have worked in
transformed lives of thousands of women
in tech
worldwide men too
and because there are a few of you who
may need a little more convincing i want
to brag
about the women in tech who've sat in
this event
exactly like you over the last three
years
recognize that if i can do it they can
do it too and put
the tenants of the framework to work
santhi attended an event just like this
at her company an international computer
maker
just two years ago she's a solutions
architect she was doing fine in her
career at the time but she recognized
she could be doing more when she heard
about taking action and stepping up she
recognized
that she needed to do that that day she
went up to her senior vice president
at the event and told him that she
wanted to pursue
a career in leadership at the company
the next thing you know
she's part of the company's worldwide
emerging leaders program
they competed in teams within the
program and her team
won so not only did they win out of top
performers but their
their project got integrated into the
comforters customer
service lot customer experience service
line
she got trained as a global ambassador
for the company
and she's also a mentor to local uh to
local girls
at as part of a women's network in her
town
but santi's story doesn't just end with
her
her husband her husband saw the results
she was getting
by just simply taking action and
stepping up and owning her outcome
that he decided to pursue a job a
stretch job promotion that he had been
avoiding
and he got it so taking action not only
changed santi's life but it changed her
husband's life
as well lynn had been out of the
workforce for a number of years not only
that but she had just moved
to a new town and she she she was really
nervous
about getting back into tech and she
didn't know how she was going to do it
but she
she she recognized the power of building
her network before she needed it so she
started attending local women's groups
and one of the women's groups said there
was going to be a hackathon to
participate in that was virtual and she
was nervous at first to participate in
the hackathon because her skills were
were out a little bit out of date but
she remembered just show up so she did
and she was on a team with women
internationally
and she discovered that she actually
knew more some of the other women she
was teaching them
and then their team ended up winning
seventh place in an international
hackathon
and now she she's putting to action and
putting herself
out there and she she's really owned her
space as a business developer
uh a business intelligence developer and
is has the confidence to go out and get
the job that she was afraid to even
apply for before
linda saw me speak at a google event
just like this one a year and a half ago
and she had a light bulb moment when i
talked about learning new and valuable
skills and jumping to the front of the
line and that day
she decided that she was going to pursue
getting her certification
in google cloud architecture and then
one of her
one of her friends called her up and
said hey we have a google cloud project
that we're working on i'd love you to be
part of the team and she almost didn't
join because she was so nervous but then
she remembered
to build your portfolio before you're
ready
and to start showing that you had those
skills and once she joined the team she
discovered that she actually knew more
than
other people and was helping them learn
and on top of that she got
paid to learn and now she's taking the
google cloud architecture exam in her
third language and is really excited
about her future because she has
opportunities because she learned from
the lying technologies
when i met barbara three years ago she
had just been laid off from a dead end
job she
she had been demoted um in part of the
great recession and
hadn't seen a race since then and she
was absolutely defeated
she hadn't known how to talk about her
value
to articulate how she could help a
company and so she recognized the value
of learning to talk about herself
building herself as a brand until she
started networking
and telling her her friends and her
family and practicing with them
and not only did she land a great job
and negotiate a great salary with a
company that values her because she did
such a great job when she got in the
door
that they even expanded her role to give
her even more
responsibility that her right in line
with her wheelhouse and her skill set
and lastly tracy tracy has this
incredible
transformation story tracy heard me
speak a number of years ago and at the
time she was she was 55
she had been on mental disability for 18
years
she was living at home with her her
parents in rural oklahoma and she
she said her own word she was lucky to
be bagging groceries at walgreens
but she recognized that that if i could
do it she could do it too so she
she started attending women in tech
networking events
started slowly relearning her her her
tech skills through online sites
and then she told people about what what
she could add value
and what kind of jobs she's looking for
a year and a half later
tracy has been working at a non-profit
in houston living on her own holding her
own
on a team of all men as a technical
project manager
and not only that but tracy said in a
developer membership
called just just a month ago she goes
lauren
i figured out that i can figure it out
and to me that was her saying i now have
confidence in myself
tracy completely transformed her life
now i've peeled back the curtain and
i've showed you what it really takes
the five simple things that i did that
all these women did too
to get ahead stand out and earn more
your career
the first thing you need to do is you
need to take action step up
show up ask even when it terrifies you
and even when you doubt yourself take
action the second thing you need to do
is build your network before you need it
figure out
who you know who should you know then go
start building
those networks internal and external one
connection at a time third thing
is constantly learn new and valuable
skills figure out where is the front of
the line
what skill sets does your employer need
does the market need
that there aren't a lot of people who
have those skills go
get those skills and build your
portfolio and when you build your
portfolio
don't do work in a silo and expect
people to notice
tell people about those skills be proud
to show off the work that you're doing
the expertise that you're building and
the impact that you're having
and the fifth and most powerful thing to
do
is invest in yourself invest in yourself
invest in your career and invest in the
life that you want for yourself
and your family now
if you want to go to the next level i
have a free gift for you
i talked about the power of the
developer at a girl journal to track
your accomplishments
to track your progress to build your
confidence over time
and it's my free gift to you go to
developer.com
journal download the free pdf
interactive journal that will help you
track and catalog your accomplishments
give you guided reflections so that you
can reflect on your accomplishments
this will help you build build your
resume build your linkedin profile
talk about yourself in performance
reviews and in interviews
and really help you build and track your
confidence over time
and if you want to go further if you
want to dive
even deeper into
all the five steps i wrote a book and
i'm excited to share it
launched this last monday on
international women's day it's based on
everything that i just talked about
and it is a best seller in 11 top
tech engineering ux and design
categories
it's available on amazon in both kindle
and paperback and has so many five-star
reviews that i i would love for you to
go out and get
dive in and this is some of my best work
in print format that you can dive in
and immediately start applying in your
own life
and it's my hope that that i'll be back
next year
celebrating another year of
international women's day and i won't
just be sharing my story i won't be
sharing
linda's and santi's and barbara story
but i'll be sharing your story
because you today said i'm worth it
you took action you stepped up you
started building your network
communicating your value
building your value and investing in
yourself
and you started the journey to own your
own success story
thank you and have a wonderful day
[Music]
thank you lauren for sharing your story
and expertise
now it's time to stretch let's welcome
our instructor who will be guiding us
with some moves during this break
enjoy them
[Music]
welcome to the international women's day
summit 2021 my name is coach annie
here to lead your movement break in our
session today we'll be breathing
moving and thinking intentionally to
kick start our minds and bodies for
today's focus
no matter where you are in your fitness
journey be proud of yourself for being
willing to participate
and dive into some movement with me the
intention of this session is to invite
some blood flow and movement to our neck
our shoulders our spine and even our
hips
and of course taking a nice little break
from our desk or wherever you've been
doing work this past year
i like to start each session with a
theme so today the theme is the power of
human connection
there's links between connecting with
others whether it's talking on the phone
or online however you connect with
others in longevity of life
so whenever you're feeling love or
empathy or connection
that's when there's chemical in our
brain that's released called oxytocin
that reduces inflammation and actually
boosts your mood so without further ado
let's go ahead connect a little bit
and get into our movement break so
joining me in a standing or seated
position however you're feeling this
moment
we're going to start with some breathing
so putting one hand on your chest one
hand on your tummy
all right hands move together with the
inhale and exhale
so really focusing on elongating that
exhale
you can breathe your mouth open or
closed
three more here
relaxing those shoulders
all right last one longest exhale
all right moving now to our neck we're
going to go into neck circles so it
doesn't matter which start which
direction you start with
but dropping that same ear to that same
shoulder
thinking about your head drawing a big
circle in the sky
body is just feeling weightless here
relaxing that jaw
go ahead and give me one more this
direction big circle
all right let's go ahead go the other
direction same thing
drop that ear to that shoulder
nice big circle
taking your time
noticing if there's any tight spots
working around it
last one here
all right shake that out a little bit
we're going to move on to our shoulders
now
going into shoulder circles so starting
forward i want you to be real dramatic
with it
open up that chest as you roll those
shoulders back
and through big inhale
long exhale giving yourself a nice
little massage here
last one this direction
all right let's balance that out go in
reverse go back now
open up that chest
give me two more here
feels good so moving on now to our spine
so i'm going to show this from the side
sewing from the standing position first
i'm going to tuck roll
my knees are going to bend as i come
down i'm going to press
my hand into my leg and open up
to one side getting some rotation take a
deep breath here
back to center and then switch to the
other side
not forcing anything here all right so
if you're standing continuing to do so
if you're seated it's the same thing
you're pressing same hand
or same arm into your leg and then
opening up like a book
getting some mobility in that middle
part of our spine which is where a lot
of our movement comes from
go ahead and give me one more each
direction
noticing with each rep if you're able to
get a little bit more rotation
all right awesome so moving on now
to our hips we're going to go into a hip
shift all right
so thinking using your imagination if
you're standing
you're going to send your hips back like
your seat sitting in a chair
all right so send one hip back you're
going to go ahead
reach for that foot and then drive
through the heel as you come back up
all right so alternating side to side
here
you're gonna sync up your breath inhale
down exhale
back up so if you're standing continuing
to do so if you are seated
a little bit different here now you're
going to shift so
one knee comes forward the other knee
comes back you're going to reach
for that opposite foot and then come
back up and then switch to the other
side so opening up this back hip
all right either you're standing or
seated same thing here
mobilizing that hip a little bit this is
a great way
if you're going for a walk or running
just feeling really tight in your hips
this is a great way to open up
all right give yourself a little bit
more mobility
go ahead and give me one more each side
last one here
all right beautiful last thing we're
gonna do for the day
some cactus arms alright so really
opening up that chest
relaxing that neck just a little bit
more meet me with your hands down to
your sides give me a big inhale up
grab those imaginary ropes and then
exhale
bring those fists to your shoulders all
right give me three more here
inhale up
exhale down
elongate that exhale bring it up
and down
last one here inhale up
and exhale down
all right awesome go ahead make your way
back to your seat or your desk all right
i hope this movement break has your mind
and body prepped let's go ahead and go
down to our neck
going to some yeses nose and i don't
knows so starting off with some yeses
here
going up and down not forcing anything
just let your body
feel weightless
breathing it out
go ahead and give me one more here
let's go in to some nose next all right
again
going within your range of motion not
forcing anything
noticing if one side's a little tighter
than the other
you can always hold it and breathe into
it
one more each side
all right last piece here i don't know
so dropping
same ear to same shoulder side
to side here trying not to shrug up your
shoulder but
meeting your head to your shoulder
instead
let's go do one more each side
all right so if you're standing keep
going into those tuck and rolls for
those who are seated
it's the same idea but if you want to
keep your legs there to
lead as some guidance for your chest or
if you want to bring your legs apart so
you can go a little bit further down
that's up to you but tucking rolling
allowing those arms just to be
weightless and then
roll back up here
and roll one vertebrae at a time
go ahead and give me three more here
going at your own pace
all right last one here
beautiful so a few more moves here
marches are next so i'm going to show
from standing first
all right it's very similar for seated
but showing from the side
thinking pushing one foot into the
ground
pulling with the other bringing that
knee up to hip level
and then coming back down
all right for those of you who are
seated same idea here
pushing through the ground pulling the
other knee up to hip level
all right opposite arm opposite leg here
feeling that stretch in your hip flexor
especially as you come up
and then lower back down can live here
for a moment at the top if you'd like
get a little extra stretch in
go ahead and give me one more each side
last one here
all right beautiful so last moon for the
day we're going to go into some
cactus arms opening up that chest a
little bit relaxing that neck even more
all right so joining me with your hands
to your sides give me a big
inhale up once those arms are up over
your head pretend you're pulling down
imaginary ropes as you exhale
long exhale three more here inhale up
exhale down
bring it up again
and down
last one here longest exhale
all right awesome making your way back
to your seats
all right and back to your desks i hope
this movement break has your mind and
body prepped
to take on the day remember that you can
use these moves daily whenever you just
need to take a nice little break
or just need to regain some focus and
attention if you like this and you're
looking for more movement in your day
i invite you to check out go hmp at home
for all of your health
and wellness needs thank you so much for
coming in i hope you enjoyed it just as
much as i did
have a great rest of your day bye for
now
[Music]
[Applause]
all right hope you all had a good break
now how many of you here are designers
i'm really excited to hand it over to
janine lee
who will be talking about diving into
design thinking
let's welcome her
[Music]
hi everyone my name is janine lee and i
will be your speaker today for diving
into design thinking
i am a global learning and development
manager for the google data center
organization
and also part-time adjunct faculty and
doctoral candidate
so a little bit about me before i get
started
i like to share this in what i call the
river of life
you can do this exercise with your team
and basically you talk about kind of
your journey and what brought you to
where you are today
typically for the river of life you can
have one side that talks about personal
and one side that talks about
professional
and kind of showing where things
intersect but this is just kind of a
high level
overview that i'll start with today so i
was born and raised in oakland
california
my parents are both immigrants the
united states my mom is from macau my
dad is from hong kong and that's me in
the bottom left corner that you see
there
along with my little brother i went to
uc davis for my undergrad
and i first started in the utility
industry and actually pivoted
to tech which was kind of unheard of
actually it's a very small percentage of
folks that can move from energy
and utility actually into the tech world
i had an emphasis and a focus on
continuous improvement
and process improvement where a lot of
design thinking principles were used
in really brainstorming and solving
complex problems
and then i did my part-time mba at the
haas school of business
where i'm now lecturing part-time in
international business leadership and
communications
and then also started teaching at the
berkeley center of executive ed in
digital transformation
and leadership communications at santa
clara university
throughout this journey coaching and
leadership was always a passion of mine
so i also got my coaching certification
at the berkeley executive coaching
institute and then now
i'm pursuing my doctorate at usc in the
school of education of rossiere
design thinking is something that didn't
originally come naturally to me it's
something that i had to learn
over time and i'm currently studying it
in my doctorate and also
launching innovation programs within my
role at google
but i'm very happy to be here today to
share with you all
what i know about design thinking
so what are we going to talk about today
i'm going to go over just briefly
what is design thinking what's the
design thinking process
some best practices for enhancing your
design thinking skills and just a
summary
and ending of the presentation
so what is design thinking
well design thinking can be described as
a discipline that uses the designer
sensibility
and methods to match people's needs with
what is technologically
feasible and what a viable business
strategy can convert into customer value
and market opportunity so this quote is
from tim brown who is the ceo of
ido and for those of you that aren't
familiar with ideo
it stands for the innovation design
engineering organization
which is one of the top organizations in
the world
that focus on innovation ultimately what
i want to highlight here is that design
thinking is a process
that starts with the end user or the
customer in mind
essentially what is the job to be done
and what problem are you solving for the
customer
and then looking at what is actually
feasible and viable and aligned with
your company's strategy
to ultimately make this a value add for
the customer and the market
so you'll hear me talk about design
thinking and innovation
interchangeably throughout this
presentation
so innovation is really the end
phenomenon when things are introduced to
the world
but everything really starts with design
thinking
and again that's the specific approach
that i'll talk about today to conceiving
the ideas for innovation
that ultimately move into the innovation
process
so both of them use similar methods they
use similar mindsets methods and tools
but typically for innovation we call it
customer-centric
whereas in design thinking we call it
user-centric
and the difference really lies between
the focus on the people
there is a very thin line between user
versus customer and we'll talk a little
bit more about that
another clarification that i want to
make is around invention versus
innovation
invention is essentially a new concept
or a product
you can invent something and get a
patent which is really cool
but to take that to the next level and
actually turn it into an innovation
we'll actually need you to be more
customer-centric and to actually
commercialize the
invention so here i have an example of a
company called ship
they started as an on-demand shipping
company
basically they found the customers needs
to ship products
the users would take a picture of the
object they want to ship
through a smartphone app and essentially
the courier would arrive
and help pack these objects box them up
and then ship them to whatever
destination
it was a really great idea and they were
able to secure funding of
up to 63 million dollars but ultimately
their profitability and their pricing
model didn't work so it wasn't a
profitable business
the company decided to charge customers
a five dollar flat fee
to basically collect and package the
items that the customer might have
and that was really one of the major
problems so it didn't really make
financial sense to charge five dollars
for everything uh whether it was a small
book or if it was a tv or a bicycle
and after a while they realized that
their pricing model
wasn't going to work for them and they
changed the pricing model to range from
three dollars to 75 dollars
ultimately with their vc funding there
was a lot of pressure to expand and they
expanded too quickly
and the cost of operations was too high
so
ultimately the company wasn't able to
sustain um
and the ceo kevin gibbon said
you know this business should exist it
ultimately should customers loved it
small businesses loved it but we didn't
focus enough on the financial
sustainability of the business from day
one
so in this example there was an
inability to transform
this from an invention to an idea and
they weren't able to meet the user's
needs while making it profitable
so this is something that we need to
continue keeping in mind as we go
through
design thinking and the differentiation
between an invention
versus an innovation so now it's time
for mythbusters
[Music]
all right so who out there watches
mythbusters i really like this show
myself we're gonna play a little game
and think about some common myths
regarding design thinking and innovation
and i'll be quoting myths from
explaining creativity by dr keith sawyer
who's a psychologist and leading
creativity researcher
so first question innovation is a skill
that can be learned true or
false so the answer is true i think i
talked about this in the beginning in my
introduction
and i'll talk a little bit more about
fixed mindset and growth mindset later
but it's definitely something that you
can learn
it's not something that you're
essentially born with
um the second question those who have no
knowledge about an area are in the best
place to create
so this is an interesting one
that is actually false so most
ideas actually come from people who are
deeply familiar with the domain
so i'm going to talk a little bit more
about t-shaped later on
and how you can be deep in domain
knowledge but have breadth of high level
knowledge
but this is essentially a myth so
if you're coming in as an outsider and
coming up with a brilliant idea that's
great
however to create the best creative
ideas
those are the people that really have
the deep domain experience that it
requires
so the third question creativity is best
when you are
alone that is actually also
false so teamwork and collaboration is
extremely critical to creativity
ideas come in conversation and creative
people
are connected to other experts and
professionals so you aren't expected to
be a professional in everything
or an expert in everything and that's
why teams
and collaboration is so critical to
creativity
all right the fourth question creativity
comes through a sudden burst of insight
so have you ever had that aha moment
where you think you suddenly have a
great idea
well that's also actually a myth and
that is false
so scientists have actually discovered
that creativity
is mostly conscious hard work so there
are times when ideas
may come suddenly but for the most part
it's actually a conscious stream of
thought and is intentional
and the last question insights come
during downtime that is actually true
the power of pausing and getting to rest
to actually connect your thoughts is so
essential to creativity
and design thinking there was an article
i read recently on innovation
where the chief of staff of one of our
former presidents
actually set time aside for our
president to think
and that was the most meaningful time to
digest the day
make decisions and ultimately that is
where the most
brilliant innovative ideas came from our
former presidents
so if you got all five right
please raise your hand and i know this
is a virtual audience so unfortunately
if we were in person i would be giving
you some type of swag because that's
what we like to do at google
but instead if you got all five right
you can raise your hand
and give yourself a nice pat on the back
and i'll give you a virtual five
high five uh great work for those of you
that got those right
so moving on to the actual design
thinking
process itself now that you know what
design thinking is
um so this framework was popularized by
stanford design school
and it was originally based on what's
called the scientific method
david kelly who's the co-founder of ido
and the founder of stanford design
school
actually introduced empathy into the
scientific method and then this is how
the design thinking process was born
it was really created as a way to make
the creative process
repeatable and a systematic approach to
solving problems
so there is this hyper focus in the user
and truly empathizing
with what the user is doing how they're
using a product
and i'm going to watch walk through each
and every one of these steps
um the cool thing about this process is
it really works for any industry or
product um so starting from left to
right
the first phase is empathizing so really
understanding the human's needs
the second phase is defining so
reframing and defining the framework
the third one is ideating so creating
many ideas
in ideation sessions the fourth is
prototyping so
how do you get a hands-on approach and
then the fifth is testing
so i'm going to be going into some more
detail about each of the subsequent
phases
so the first one is empathizing
and for those of you that are very
familiar with empathizing
you know empathy is our ability to see
the world through other people's eyes
to really see what they see feel what
they feel
and experience things as they would of
course
none of us can really truly fully
experience things someone else does
but we can attempt to get as close as
possible
so you can do this from a variety of
different ways and i'm going to go
through them one by one
the first is being a good listener
haven't you ever felt like you were
going through a situation and you just
said
i wish someone would just listen to me
and they would understand how i'm
feeling i don't need somebody to give me
advice
well that's extremely critical in step
one is to really listen to your end user
your customer
what are they feeling and what are they
um experiencing
the second one is to observe them so
instead of just
listening to them what do you see them
doing
if you ever like to people watch this is
most certainly
the best opportunity to do that so if
you go into a store for example
and you see how an end user interacts
with a product
or what they're ordering on the menu
from those insights you can
really help understand and empathize
what the customer wants and what the
customer needs
the third thing you can do is
questioning so
what do our customers need and how do
they do things today
and why do they need this and what are
they using today to solve the problem
there's all sorts of questions that you
can ask
the one technique that i love leveraging
the most
is called five wise so really peeling
back the onion of
why so why did you purchase this product
because my sister told me that it was a
great product
well why did your sister think it was
such a great product so after asking
five whys you get really down to the
root cause or the root question
and that is a technique that you can use
as you're interacting with your
customers
or even trying to better understand a
problem or a solution that you're trying
to solve
the fourth thing is conducting
interviews and again
leveraging the being a good listener
observing and questioning
are really critical in this so really
going out there talking to your end
customers
talking to your consumers and figuring
out
what it is that they need the fifth
thing is
creating user journey maps so how can
you understand what a customer is doing
day to day
how do they spend their day when they
get up till the end of the day
or when they're shopping what are their
habits when they first go into the mall
which store do they go to first
what do they have to do to stand in line
what do they have to do to check out
those would all be things that you could
potentially do to understand the user
journey and what the user is going
through
the last thing is called body storming
and that is the act of physically
experiencing a situation
in order to immerse oneself fully in the
user's environment
so how might you do that or do you have
examples in which
you might have done that in the past so
once i was at a fair and i saw
the organization mad which is the
mothers that are against drunk driving
and they had these goggles that you put
on and i remember putting them on
and it was literally the act of
physically experiencing what it was like
to be drunk
the goggles were so distorted you
couldn't walk straight
you couldn't pick anything up and it
really was body storming it was
really putting you in those user shoes
but if for example you were targeting
products
towards specific user groups those who
are blind those who can't hear
body storming would essentially put you
into that persona
and try to build inclusive products and
try to understand what the user is going
through
so that's step one empathize and some of
the tools that you could use to go
through this step
the second step is around defining
so i'm going to start with the quote
that you see here
upgrade your user not your product don't
build better cameras
build better photographers that was
stated by kathy sierra who is a
programming
instructor and game designer so what
she's saying here is really critical
so what are people actually buying so in
the instance of a camera
they're not really buying a camera
they're buying a way to capture a photo
or capture a memory
and if you were only thinking about
building better cameras you would miss
out on this incredible opportunity in
the market which is that
predominantly smartphones have replaced
cameras and they can do
many things that cameras can do
all in one so a lot of times you really
need to think about
what is the job to be done which is the
jtvd so when people buy drills
they're not buying a drill they're
buying a whole so essentially
thinking about what is that the job
needs to be
that's performed by the customer that
will help you kind of zone out in
thinking about and defining the problem
and what it is to be solved so what is
it exactly that the customer is solving
what are they trying to do with the
product
and in some instances it can be multiple
things
from there what i would do is actually
draft your problem statement
it's extremely critical to actually
write down what is the problem that's
trying to be solved for the customer
and then step three would be to verify
your problem
i can't emphasize how important it is to
understand what the problem is
that you're trying to solve and who do
you need to verify the problem with
yeah that's right the user the end user
the customer
and maybe your boss or your director
when you're
working in a in a corporate environment
but you just want to make sure you're
solving the right problem
because a lot of people spend a lot of
time going down a rabbit hole
solving a problem that either doesn't
exist or is actually
the wrong problem for a customer
so that concludes step two define
and we'll move into step three ideate
which is the most fun part of this whole
process
so creating many ideas
in multiple sessions how do we come up
with the best ideas and again
this is with the premise that you have
the right problem statement
and that you know what you're solving so
the first thing
you can do is brainstorming how might we
so for example how might we create a
faster way for customers to receive
their packages
well amazon has done that with amazon
prime
it's efficient it's fast it's two day
shipping so
how might we you can ask that question
amongst your team
you can ask that question as you're
solving your problem and reflecting on
your problem statement
the third thing is contradiction without
compromise so that is
actually a slogan that's been my friend
in thinking about creating the best
solutions
so how do you think of something that is
a contradiction without compromising so
the example i like to use is a
zero calorie cupcake that tastes good
so that sounds like a complete
contradiction how can you have
a delicious cupcake that's zero calories
but that is the contradiction without
compromising so if you can come up with
an idea
that really is this contradiction
without compromising at all
you'll have the opportunity to come up
with a phenomenal idea
and throughout all of this your number
one tool is really post-its
so i cannot emphasize enough how
post-its are used for brainstorming
and i used to carry around a bag of
post-its and markers with me everywhere
just to come up with ideas and put them
together and so
rapid brainstorming coming up with as
many
ideas as you can good ideas as you can
using post-its
are generally encouraged and then you
can do what i call affinitize
them so group them together into themes
circle them look at trends and have a
discussion and i know that's much more
challenging to do with your teams in
this environment
but google has a great tool that you
could use called jamboard
you could virtually use post-its you can
post them around
and have people build upon each other's
ideas and you can affinitize them and
group them into
bigger ideas as you go along some other
techniques i've used is doing the
opposite of the worst idea
i know that sounds a little confusing
but for example
if you were to fail at having the worst
car
ever how might you do the opposite so
what would
the worst car look like in the world
it's probably
not very good looking it's hard to park
so you'd have all that functionality
laid out
and then your idea would be the opposite
so for example
if you don't want a car that's difficult
to park you would say
well let's design a car that's super
easy to park
and nowadays someone has already ideated
this
but we have those auto parking cars that
auto parallel park and how cool is that
you press a button
and the car auto parks for you um so you
can use
this opposite of the worst idea for
brainstorming
and then the last one is around building
upon ideas
so again um brainstorming is best in
teams and design thinking and innovation
works best in teams
so you could take a piece of paper write
down
an idea sit in a circle pass the paper
around
and build upon someone's idea so again
focused on the same problem
someone may come up with one idea passes
it to you and each person
builds the idea to make it even better
i know that that's challenging again in
a coveted environment but you can do
this in a spreadsheet you could use a
jamboard
come up with specific ideas and then
call a rotation
for those ideas and hand off those ideas
to the next person
and i guarantee you with any of these
tactics you'll come up with some amazing
ideas
moving on to step four prototyping
so prototyping is really adopting a
hands-on approach
and it really the goal is to make your
ideas as real as possible
so let's say you have no budget it's
okay
i've categorized this from the least
costly and least risky
to the most costly or the most hands-on
so let's start with the story you can
create a story
of your idea from the future so what
would the experience be like
you can write a newspaper article
or you can write just a story someone
can read to say
imagine a world where you have
xyz product that you use that
automatically helps you cook your dinner
and this is how it does it this is how
long it takes and so forth
so it's it's kind of like a pitch but
it's really creating a story of
how someone would use this product and
how you would visualize it and that
helps you think about
other aspects of this product or idea
the second area is an advertisement so
taking that a step further if you were
to then take this story into an
advertisement
if you had some graphics you promote
your idea and you have fun with it
who would that advertisement appeal to
what customers you could even spend the
money
to put this advertisement in a newspaper
or online
and see who reaches out and see how much
people might enjoy this product so it's
a real world way to do this without
having to actually create a product
the next one is a user journey or role
play
so it's really thinking about acting out
your idea
so trying out the role of the customer
or the people in the situation
and uncovering questions that they might
ask you
so you could assemble simple props
uniforms you could record it in this
virtual environment you could play
multiple roles
but what would the customer do for
example if they showed up at the store
or if they were in line at the grocery
market
how would they utilize this product or
how would this product shift
around so really looking into this
role-playing user journey
to really act out the experience and if
you're not able to do the role play you
could do
an actual user journey that's drawn out
with stick figures to
say this is the customer this is where
the customer would go
this is the journey that they would have
in this experience which leads me to the
next idea
which is a diagram or a process map so
you can map out the structure the
network the journey or the process of
your idea
and you can try different versions so
diagrams can be especially helpful
to share a service that you're imagining
or
a process that you're redoing to really
think through
what would this look like and it gives
you flexibility to reconfigure and
get feedback um going a step further
you could create a mock-up you can
actually sketch out
mock-ups of digital tools or apps or
websites
you could simply do a sketch on a piece
of paper and
tape it to a computer screen or a mobile
phone
and ask your friends ask your end
customers
if you were to see this app or you were
to see this on a screen what would you
click
where would you go next all right here's
the next piece of paper
um so it doesn't have to be super
polished or super professional but if
you do have the budget
of course doing actually a ux design and
a ux
session and actually looking through
prototype apps and seeing how users
interface with
a phone app or on a computer would be
the next level of that
and then lastly 3d models so
it could be a three-dimensional
representation of your idea
using cardboard fabric whatever it is
whatever you can find to really just
show the size of the model what the
model might look like
and if you don't want to be so scrappy
you can actually
hire someone to do a 3d printing of your
model and
actually look and touch and feel what
your product might look like
so any of these ideas are viable for how
you want a prototype and everyone's
going to do it differently
depending on your risk level and budget
that you might have
and lastly testing so developing
your prototype or your solution and
actually testing it with the end user
you want to know
did this solve your problem the purpose
is really to get feedback
and failures are okay and i will talk
more about failures later
but the key is to keep iterating and
refining
and to going back to the prototype phase
if you need
or going all the way back to id8 if what
you created doesn't solve the problem
so again even though it's a linear
process with five steps
you go back into multiple phases as
needed so i would highly
encourage you to test as much as you can
and as much as you're comfortable with
get as much feedback and be okay with
failing
or having to iterate and going back um
into time and
many of our famous inventors many that
have gone through the design thinking
process take a long time to go through
and actually complete the last step
because they're really refining coming
up with a product that really meets the
end user's needs
so lastly we've gone through what is
design thinking
what is the design thinking process uh
what are the best practices or how can
you become
incredibly well-versed in design
thinking well
i really love food so i always have to
do something with a food bean and i do
like spicy food
so i've come up with four different ways
that you could depend on depending on
your comfort level
begin to flex your design thinking
mindset
so starting with mild and going to spicy
it depends on your spiciness level
and your tolerance for spice so i'll be
referencing professor
carol dweck's fixed mindset and growth
mindset
um article in this discussion
so i'll talk a little bit more about how
to move from this fixed mindset to this
growth mindset
so the first thing that you can do and
this is a mild
spiciness is to really build your
discovery skills
and i'm referencing here the innovator's
dna which is one of the
books that i'm reading in my doctorate
and it really makes innovators different
if you're able to build out these skills
so starting on the left side
the first piece is the courage and the
mindset
so are you number one willing to
challenge the status quo
and to take risks and you know
potentially fail
so many of you may say yes i want to i
want to change my mindset i do
have the courage i definitely am into
design thinking that's why i'm watching
this on a saturday
and i'm really excited to hear about
this topic great
we've checked the box on that um then
we'll move into the behavioral skills
so we talked about questioning we talked
about observing
and then moving into networking and
experimenting
so how can you network whether it be
socially or connecting things together
associating different ideas metaphors
how people are solving complex problems
across
other industries and how those apply to
your industry
those are all part of the cognitive
skills so taking the behavioral skills
and moving it into this deep thought of
the cognitive
skills and then moving into innovation
so those would all be skills that i
would recommend
in the mild spiciness range and one of
the things that you can leverage
to remember the acronym for this is
q-o-nea
so q-o-n-e-a are you questioning are you
observing
are you networking are you experimenting
and are you associating
you'll want to make that as part of your
regular language as much as possible
as you're building out your discovery
skills
the next step in your level of spiciness
to progress from mild to medium is
really to be
t shaped so ideo came up with this
um t-shaped philosophy to be a t-shaped
person
what does that mean well we talked a lot
about having deep subject matter
expertise
to be creative and to really think about
a creative mindset so that depth and
knowledge can be anything
and so i would challenge you to think
about what is your
deep expertise in it's one knowledge
area
specifically it could be something like
design
it could be engineering it could be
communications it can be something that
you are known as an expert in and that
is something you have deep expertise in
and would be incredibly innovative
to create new ideas the second thing
is the other part of the t-shape which
is a base knowledge and skill
so thinking about not just depth but
thinking about
a broad range across marketing finance
um legal compliance so having some
high level visibility and understanding
of
your company or the product area or the
industry that you're in
and again this is really where the
teamwork and collaboration plays such an
important role
because you want to be able to leverage
that network and
get more depth from those who are
t-shaped in that specific area
so if you want to up your spiciness
level think about
what is the deep expertise that you have
already or that you want to gain in a
specific area
and how can you more broadly understand
knowledge across different areas
that would be what t-shaped is
and now we're moving into a next level
of spiciness
so this is the start of spicy
forming a brain truss so what is a brain
trust i'm referencing this from the book
creativity inc who was co-authored by
edwin catmull
who is the co-founder of pixar and
there is one key mechanism that pixar
uses time and time again and it's called
the brain trust
so every few months there's a meeting
and people get together and they talk
openly about the progress of their
movies and the goal
is very simple it's to put smart and
passionate people in a room
give them a problem and encourage them
to be honest and open with one another
so people feel obligated to be honest
and are usually more open and genuine in
the room and they can express
themselves openly and so creating that
climate to do that
and really there's no authority in the
room so everyone is supposed to be an
equal in this meeting
but the main element is of course
honesty and that is the essence
so leveraging this benchmark from pixar
who's one of the most creative companies
in the world
you can form a brain trust with your
team and in fact
when pixar and disney merged they formed
another brain trust on the disney side
because it was so successful in pixar
so i would challenge you to think about
how you can create an environment with
unfiltered criticism and honesty and
really broaden your perspective
bringing your ideas forward to your team
people you trust
in an environment that's safe to talk
about the ideas build upon them
and really take your ideas to the next
level
and lastly sharing your failures
this is the ultimate spiciness level
um and this is really hard to do uh i
myself have a fear of failure and so
it's very hard for me to talk about
failure
however if you can really embrace your
challenges and failures this
really takes your creative thinking to
another level
the first thing you need to do is really
embrace the challenges that come along
so we talked about the design thinking
process and how
you will be ideating and prototyping and
testing with your customer and
oftentimes it'll fail
so when those things happen how do you
embrace that challenge how do you pivot
how do you revise your idea and how do
you persist
right there will be obstacles and
setbacks in the design thinking process
and it's really up to you and your team
to continue moving forward
um to continue thinking ahead um
learning from the criticism and
adjusting
and ultimately you really do want to
build a customer a culture
excuse me that feels fast so how do you
fail fast in an idea learn something
get best practices and move forward
that is something that's very
challenging for companies to do and
teams to do especially if you're new
but ultimately the most creative
companies and people
are in the cultures with psychological
safety and that's ultimately
what you want to increase in your team
to increase creativity and design
thinking
and so i talked about the brain trust
the brain trust cannot be successful
without a level of psychological safety
so really getting to this ultimate
spiciness level
is where you're going to be able to
learn from your failures fail fast
move forward to the next idea and learn
from it without
um holding someone specifically
accountable or pointing
fingers at somebody for the failure um
so this is again the deepest thing that
you can do to really
increase and have a best practice of
design thinking
so some homework for you i would not be
a lecturer or professor without giving
you some
so write this down create your failure
resume
what was one of your biggest failures
and what did you learn from it
and specifically dig deep right
what was something in in life that you
want to reflect on or in your career
and what did you really learn about
yourself
um your interests and
to take it a step further if you're
comfortable
i would challenge you to share this with
someone
whether it's a friend a family member a
colleague you trust or even in a team
environment
we just did an icebreaker not that long
ago within my team
and the question that came up was what's
a mistake that you made recently
and sharing it with the team and i was
so surprised
how authentic and vulnerable everyone
was in the team with
sharing of what it was that they failed
at and
we learned so much from that opportunity
so i would encourage you
if you want to be super spicy to go
forward with
writing your failure and sharing it with
your team
so in summary what did we learn today
our theme is courage to create and i
hope that you all have the courage to
create and dive into design thinking as
a result of this presentation
so what is design thinking we talked
about it being a process
that ultimately starts with the end user
or the customer and keeping the customer
in mind throughout the end-to-end
process
design thinking ultimately leads to
innovation and again
invention and innovations are not the
same thing
um what is the design thinking process
so we talked about that
empathizing defining ideating
prototyping and testing
and i talked through with you some of
the techniques that you could use in
each of the phases as you move your
product or your idea
down the design thinking process and
then lastly
how do you become a better innovator or
how do you become a better design
thinker
we talked about the different for
spiciness levels
so again building your discovery skills
looking at the keonea
and focusing on those skills moving from
behavioral to cognitive skills and
ultimately to innovation
we talked about becoming t-shaped so
again thinking about what you want to
have
deep technical expertise in and then
keeping in mind the breadth of knowledge
across the other pillars and the other
areas in your team and networking with
your team
and then third we talked about forming a
brain trust so really thinking about
how you can bring a collaborative group
of people together similar to pixar
to really talk through your ideas ideas
and build upon one another
and lastly the sharing your failure
so encouraging you to take the homework
assignment that i gave you
and really thinking about a time that
you may have failed
and even taking a step further if you
can
to share your failures with someone and
that ultimately will help you become a
better innovator and your colleagues
and to build psychological safety and
trust
so thank you so much for having me today
it was an honor to present
keep it spicy so think about how spicy
you want to be
and if you want to stay in touch please
feel free to connect with me on linkedin
thank you
[Music]
thank you janine that was great now
for those who are interested in building
your first android app
we have a session just for you let's
welcome megan meta
who who will be talking about how to
build your first android app
hi i'm megan metta a developer advocate
on the android team
happy international women's day i'm so
excited to be here and show you
how to build your first android app with
kotlin
before we get started who am i why am i
talking to you about this
i've been at google on the android team
for two years i'm a usc graduate with a
degree in computer science
an opera singer and a lover of improv
and sketch comedy
our talk today assumes that you have
basic knowledge of the kotlin
programming language
and android studio if you don't have
either of these don't worry
still watch the talk see how the app
comes together and then use the
resources i'll give you
to get up to speed
so what are we making today
we are making a dice roller app when you
press the button
it will generate a random number from 1
to six
so let's get started if you don't
already have android studio downloaded
make sure you download it i have the
link
right there and once you're in android
studio
we're going to create a new project
we're going to choose an empty activity
we're going to name it dice roller make
sure the language is kotlin and make
sure the minimum sdk is api
19.
now that you've done that we're going to
create an emulator if you have not
already created one
so on android studio we're going to go
to tools and then click avd manager
from there we'll click create virtual
device
choose a pixel 4
choose r as a system image you might
have to download this
you can give it a fun name but other
than that just keep the defaults here
and now that you have a shiny new
emulator
you can press the play button on the top
pane
and your emulator will show
a blank application that says hello
world
congrats you ran your first android app
so this isn't the android app that we're
creating in the talk
um so let's let's get into that let's
let's figure out what it's going to look
like
on the left pane we're going to go into
the res folder
into the layout folder and then click on
activity main
dot xml
you'll see something that looks like
this
cool what did we just do so what we just
did is we
clicked on the text that said hello
world and we updated it to say iwd
2021 then we scroll down and we made the
text bigger
when we run the app like we ran it
before let's see what it'll look like
now instead of hello world you have a
larger text and you have it saying iwd
2021. you can play around with that you
can change the text
to say whatever you want you can have it
say your name your best friend's name
anything
so now that we have iwd 2021
we want to add in the button
great so what we just did is we took a
button from the palette which has
different views that you can use
we dragged it in and we changed the text
to say
roll dice now let's run the app and see
what happens
okay so it looks like the view is
showing up in the
top left corner this is because we
haven't specified where we want it to be
placed
the initial text has a default of being
in the middle of the screen
so now we have to specify where we want
our button to be
we want the button to be below our text
that says iwd
2021 and we want it to be centered
to do this we're going to hold the white
circle with blue border and drag it all
the way to the right
and then we're going to take the left
circle and take it all the way to the
left
this is going to center the view next
you're going to take the top edge
and drag it to the bottom of the iwd
text now
run your code
yay you have it centered and right under
the iwd text
right where we want it
now we're going to click on the button
and on on the right pane we're going to
give it an id
of button this pane will pop up and
we're going to click refactor
and we're going to do the same thing
with the text view we're going to
give it an id of text view refactor it
and refactor it for that
now you'll notice on the top right that
there's
three things it says code split design
and we're currently on the design tab so
if you go over and click on the code tab
you'll see that some code has been
generated for you there's a text view
and a button just like we had in the
design tab
this is code that's generated whenever
we change anything on the design tab
so as you can see the text has says iwd
2021 on the text view
the text size is 30 as we updated it to
be
and the id is text view now for the
button we have an id of button
a text of roll dice and you can see that
the constraints are as we set them
as you can see the constraint is the end
of it is constrained to the end of the
parent
the start of it is constrained to the
start of the parent and it's constrained
to the bottom of the text view
this is what we did earlier when we took
the right and
dragged it all the way to the right we
took the left and dragged it all the way
to the left
and then took the top and constrained it
to the bottom of the text view the next
thing we're going to do is turn
on auto imports
for mac you're going to go to file new
project settings
preferences for new projects and for
windows you're going to go to file
other settings setting for new projects
you'll make sure that add ambiguous
imports on the fly
are enabled for both
java and kotlin and also optimize
imports on the fly
are enabled for both java and kotlin
this will come in handy
in our next step so now we have
some text we have a button but we want
to make the button interactive
on the left pane open the java folder
and then open up the first folder that
says com.example.dice roller
then open up the main activity
so now we're in an activity file but
what does the activity file actually
mean
an activity provides the window which in
which your app drives its ui
in your main activity code you need to
provide details on the activities layout
and how the user should interact with it
the android system calls the oncreate
method of your main activity when your
app is open for the first time
the oncreate method sets up the main
activity by using code from imports
and by setting the starting layout with
set content view
set content view specifies and inflates
activity main as its layout
so
now we're going to want to interact with
our button so we're going to create a
value called roll button
and we're going to give it a type of
button
we're going to use something called find
view by id which is going to find a view
based on the id specified and that's why
earlier we specified the button
with an id and the text view as an id
we're going to use find view by id
type r dot id and then give it the id
of button and so now role button is
associated
to the button that we created in our
layout
at this point this is what your oncreate
code should look like
now we're going to set an on click
listener on our button and this is where
we can specify
what to do when the button is clicked
just to show what this is going to look
like very quickly we're going to use a
toast
a toast is just a way to specify text
that's really
um that pops up on the screen and so
we'll say
toast.make text this which is the
activity
dice rolled as the text and give it the
length of short
then we're going to call show on the
text so it'll show itself
is what the on click listener will look
like with the toast inside of it
and this is what the main activity will
look like with
everything together
let's see what happens
on the bottom it has a little pop-up
that says dice rolled
which is exactly what we wanted to and
it happened when we pressed the button
we have a toe showing but that's not
what really what we wanted to happen
when the button's pressed we want to
update the text above
so in the same way that we associated
the button
from the layout to the activity we're
going to do the same thing for the text
view
we're going to create a value set it as
the text view
and use find view by id with the id we
set earlier
so we have a value result text view
of type text view and we're going to use
find view by id
with the id text view which we set
earlier
just to demonstrate how this works we're
going to
set the result text view to 6 when we
press the button
make sure that you have erased the toast
uh code and now we're gonna have the
result text view in
and we're gonna set the result view text
the result textview's text to 6.
and let's see how it works
when we press the button our text turns
to six
exactly what we wanted
that's great so we have the text view
setting to six
it's what we wanted to happen with that
code
but now we want to connect the dice's
logic
this is how we generate a random number
in kotlin
what this says is generate a random
number
from the lower bound to the upper bound
the lower bound being one and the upper
bound being six
we want to set the result textview's
text to one of those random numbers
so we'll set the result textview.txt
to the number that's generated if you
type in this code right now
you'll get an error um so why is that
result text view is expecting a string
and we are giving it a number
so we have an easy fix to that
we're going to call the tostring method
on it which will convert our random
number
into the correct string format that the
result textview's text is expecting
so this is what the full code in the
main activity class should look like
and that is our final app
congratulations you built a dice roller
app
and i highly recommend learning even
more by taking the
android basics course which is online
and free
if you have never coded before if you
don't know kotlin or android at all you
can start at the very beginning
and if you learned from this and you
want to keep going
there's many more units after this of
things that you can learn
my name is megan i have you can connect
with me on instagram
i'm at a dressy engineer and
i'm so excited for your journey in
android
[Music]
thanks megan up next we have allison
kelly
sharing her story amusing on why women
are underrepresented
in stem
[Music]
hello my name is alison kelly
i am the growth marketer and engineer
of bot mock which is a small startup
about six people on the team
um yeah cool and i'll go ahead
so my story begins in 2010
when i was a transferring sophomore to
the university of illinois at chicago
i was living in a new city which meant
living this new life
becoming a new representation of myself
the anonymity
of being one amongst millions meant i
could be
anybody at all but one
bright late summer morning i walked into
my first class with confidence
and i tucked my sundress underneath my
seat
sat down turned to my neighbor and
before i could say a single word
he turns to me and he says um i think
you're in the wrong classroom
this is computer science and his words
were not
unkind and they were not malicious and
he was genuinely trying to be helpful
which he was because i was in the wrong
classroom
um but it would really take me years
before i realized the
subtle subtext of his statements
that the one thing that set me apart in
that classroom
was the fact that i was a woman and i
was literally one of two women
in the classroom and these
you know innocent but sexist
microaggressions will
plant themselves in the mind of a young
girl and they will
germinate and they will grow until we
find ourselves
battling these feelings of not belonging
the following year i found myself
sitting across the dinner table from my
boyfriend's parents for the first time
when his dad looks at me and says i bet
you're a communications major aren't you
and again nothing that had been said
that entire conversation
would have alluded to my major and he
was right
i was a communications major but it was
because i was a woman
in those two short sentences calling out
uh my otherness in a field that's
dominated by men in computer science
and another devaluing my choice
to as a woman to choose a communications
degree
they were subtle and insidious and they
caused years of damage to my confidence
as a professional
and unfortunately i know that i'm not
alone
in 2012 the year i graduated
computer science uh computer science
degrees were awarded to only 18
of women and more surprisingly that's 10
less than the year 2000 where women
earned nearly one in three computer
science degrees
and last year only about 20 percent of y
combinator winner batch
applicants were women so
there's this culmination of frequent
sexist microaggressions
that causes what's called sexism-based
traumatic stress
and researchers theorize that the
affected individuals will
internalize this discrimination and
adopt the demeaned persona
which continues to contribute to mental
health effects
such as negative self-worth this
internalized misogyny
alters our understanding of ourselves
and diminishes our ability to
support other women and i can tell you
in my early 20s the success of women i
knew
only acted to bolster my shame and
feelings of inadequacy
in my professional life and it also made
me resent them in a way
and these feelings weren't active they
weren't at the forefront of my mind
you know i outwardly celebrated them
but it wasn't until i really realized
that it wasn't my fault that i thought
this way
it's not the fault of the oppressed that
our minds gravitate
uh towards such distorted forms of
thinking
and it's not until you do realize
what's at play that you can proactively
resist internalizing
sexist microaggressions learn to heal
and
finally celebrate yourself and celebrate
your womanhood
and the professional endeavors whether
or not you're in a male-dominated field
i eventually leveraged my experience in
marketing
and my certification in data science
which was partially paid for
by a scholarship designed to bring more
women into the field
to eventually lead the growth strategy
for a small startup
small tech startup where i am now and
many of you that are listening to this
talk probably overcame the trauma that
you probably didn't even realize you had
to become successful in technology
and but how do we get to a point where
we don't need scholarships to
incentivize women to
achieve an education and technology does
it start with data science barbie
doesn't mean that you have to challenge
the assumptions of your boyfriend's dad
at the dinner table embarrassing
yourself
even though he is the one that should be
embarrassed
maybe but i believe that it starts by
just being aware of the microaggressions
which diminishes their power
and gives you more of an opportunity to
feel compassion for yourself
and with this understanding of ourselves
and our womanhood and the world around
us
we can set an example for the women and
girls in our lives
who may be struggling with it themselves
and every time i find myself feeling
intimidated by another woman's
career path i speak the words out loud
what's what an inspiration how can i be
more like her
and every time i'm crushed by the
overwhelming and
dreaded imposter syndrome i remember the
many times that colleagues have told me
that they were happy that i was on their
team
by actively acknowledging the collective
trauma
of women when it comes to our education
and professions
and teaching ourselves to have
self-compassion
we can then alter the conversation and
protect one another
and the girls that will follow in our
footsteps thank you so much for joining
my talk
and you can find me on linkedin um
my name is allison kelly
a-l-l-i-s-o-n-k-e-l-l-y
thank you
[Music]
finally our last session is coming up
join me in welcoming eleanor to talk
about how data sciences
who are also mothers of young children
are coping with school closures
and child care uncertainties during
covet 19
and what this says about our society as
a whole
let's welcome eleanor
hi my name is eleanor fournier toomes
and i'm a data scientist
i work at the world bank and as a
professor at the university of ottawa
and i'm speaking to you today about
working moms in data science during
covet 19.
just about a year ago my partner and i
received an email
from our oldest son school just like
everyone around the world
we'd been following the news with
growing anxiety
and by that time we knew what was coming
spring break was just ending and to be
honest i have
absolutely no idea of what we did did i
take time off
go sledding go to the museum i really
have no idea
all i remember is that schools closed
first for a single day
then for six weeks and then of course
for the rest of the school year
because our oldest was only in pre-k
there wasn't much that he could do
online
so once or twice a week he met with his
class for about an hour to listen to
stories
he liked to put his eye into the camera
and fall off his chair
all around the world children started
shifting to online learning
and in a lot of cases they had their
daily lesson through public televisions
any extra help that families used to
rely on evaporated
daycares nannies extracurricular sports
grandparents neighbors each one of us
was alone
in our family bubble
immediately working moms started to
raise the alarm
so before the pandemic working women in
canada already did 28 hours of domestic
work
per week 50 more than working men
in the u.s numbers were very similar
with the majority of working mothers
saying that they had more child care
responsibilities
from supervising homework to
coordinating pickup and activities to
communicating with teachers
and dealing with all kinds of
emergencies so during sick days snow
days
or pandemics women were eight times more
likely to take the day off
for work than men i actually think that
this is an underestimation for many
women
i tried to calculate how many hours i
spent with my children before the
pandemic
and i came up with 49 hours per week so
that's five hours on each weekday
and 12 hours on each weekend day and
that doesn't include nighttime wake-ups
so now that schools were closed and for
many they not available in both canada
and the us
for example the vast majority of
frontline health workers
teachers and elderly care workers are
women they've often been allowed special
child care
but have had to deal with sending young
children to unfamiliar temporary
environments i think this has been
extremely stressful for many families
newspaper outlets have started to report
that women are dropping out of the
workforce
twenty thousand canadian women left the
workforce between february and october
2020.
in the united states it was 900 000
women for
300 000 men in approximately the same
period
working moms have also begun
experiencing mental health issues
with the legion polling firm estimating
that 40 of canadian women
between the ages of 18 and 34
experienced
bad are experiencing bad or very bad
mental health
right now on the other hand
the pandemic has led to an increase in
relevance for the field of data science
everywhere there has been data analysis
how do we track
the spread of the disease measured
severity correlate co-morbidities
understand the most vulnerable predict
the impact of
non-pharmaceutical interventions
predictive closures track variance find
cures
the list goes on from december 2019 to
january 2020
and chen dong a first year phd student
at john hopkins university
heard from his family in china about the
spread of the virus
in january he started working on a case
tracking website that would soon become
one of the most visited sites of the
pandemic
many other data scientists started to
work on case analysis
pouring through the data in order to
understand how the virus spread
and what made people more vulnerable to
severe infection than others
others started developing predictive
models which showed how
non-pharmaceutical interventions like
school closures
and social distancing would impact the
case count and hospitalization rates
these models have informed policy
decisions in each country around the
world
and have created this new society that
we live in today so
seeing women in the workforce being
muzzled on the one hand
unable to work completely overwhelmed by
work
and this incredible rise in the
importance of data science and
technology to address this emergency
i ask myself what does this mean for
women in data science
what does it mean to have this
extraordinary opportunity to apply our
skills
to help solve a global crisis while at
the same time being more busy than ever
completely exhausted by an enormous
increase in household responsibilities
at the time i was working at the united
nations on the development of a model
that would predict the spread and
severity of the virus
in countries that were already in a
humanitarian crisis
like many of my colleagues and friends
who had children i developed a double
life
working shifts of one to two hours
during the day which i used mostly for
meetings
and then catching up with coding late
into the night
one of my friends told me i love my job
and i'm very good at it but i have no
bandwidth to help at all with the
pandemic right now
i'm completely powerless to seize new
opportunities and show my worth
another friend who worked as a knowledge
manager in a law firm
told me in april it has been 46 days
she was counting 46 days straight of
working in shifts
breastfeeding while on calls working
until midnight
so why is this particularly a problem
for data science
well when i teach i talk about the key
skills in data science
which i think are creativity drafting
innovative methodologies for vaguely
defined problems often with no support
precision ensuring that the data and
code have no errors
checking all the calculations and
assumptions which is a huge amount of
responsibility
focus diving into a problem and really
thinking it through
communication presenting results in an
engaging way
and leadership guiding people to jointly
implement the solution
such as other data scientists product
owners or even policy makers
but what happens when we don't have time
to think
in reality none of the things that we
just discussed are possible
or if they are it's only with great
effort
something that cannot be sustained for
one year and counting
by not adequately supporting working
mothers we have deprived ourselves of a
huge segment of the population
10 of the population in canada and the
us
are working mothers of young children
this percentage of the population have
expertise to lead the country out of the
pandemic
from the beginning governments knew that
women were adversely affected by school
closures
i actually wrote my first op-ed about
this in may and by that time hundreds of
other articles had already been written
by women trying to raise awareness to
this issue
by now thousands more have written and
spoken about the disproportionate impact
of the pandemic on women's work
mental health and economic situation
this is not a problem for each
individual woman having to manage her
work-life balance properly
this is a systemic societal issue which
existed before the pandemic
and has only gotten worse what many
don't realize i think
is that the loss of contributions from
women in the sector came at a time when
we needed them more than ever
over the last year women who have been
able to work have been recognized for
their incredible contributions to the
crisis
women like jacinda ardern the prime
minister of new zealand who is also a
working mom
and has been praised for her calm and
empathetic leadership of the country
woman like teresa tam who is a doctor in
canada's chief public health officer
and a multitude of epidemiologists
physicists and machine learning
scientists
who i have met through my work it has
been said
that women have been better able to lead
through this crisis
this chart from the harvard business
review published in december 2020
showed that women in the united states
are currently seen as more effective
leaders than men
particularly during this crisis perhaps
this is because
in order to succeed in our society women
still have to work so much harder than
men to break through the glass ceiling
and they have therefore accumulating
more skills and experience
perhaps it is also because having been
responsible for so much more care work
of children of elderly parents
and others in their lives they are much
more able to deal with the vulnerability
pain and distress
that arise during a crisis
regardless it is not too late to act
there is still plenty of work to do to
navigate through the rest of this crisis
to determine the best policies to make
it through the winter
to optimize the distribution of vaccines
to work out recovery plans that will
lead us
out of this pandemic stronger than ever
with common global commitments to
inequality
climate change and education so what can
we do about this now
first i think we need to acknowledge
that gender imbalance in domestic labor
doesn't just
affect working mothers it affects all of
society
who loses their critical skills and
leadership
maybe the pandemic would have been
better managed if we hadn't muzzled so
many working mothers during the last
year
maybe some of the women who were
struggling to tune a random forest
algorithm with a little child screaming
for a snack
right beside them could have come up
with something really innovative
so let's not continue this mistake let's
start now to make sure
we get them the time and space they need
to think
analyze and lead us through the rest of
this crisis
second we need to urgently support
working moms who are drowning right now
having burnouts and dropping out of the
workforce
and supporting them doesn't just mean
giving them some money so that they can
take time off
in many ways taking care of children
full-time particularly with this looming
economic crisis
when women have to compete for their
jobs is
actually more stressful and tiring than
working at your actual job
so it means rethinking how education and
child care will take place
providing options for nannies and
multiple family bubbles
and being generally much more creative
in how we address this issue
third i really think we need to
encourage the men that have stepped up
at home during this crisis who have done
their fair share and started to
experience what it was like to be a
working mom
all along a lot of people have said that
the crisis having the women completely
overwhelmed and burned out
have forced men to take on much more
care work than ever before
and that everyone is better for it i've
certainly seen this in my life
and i hope that this is a trend towards
equalizing household work
and finally getting rid of the woman's
second shift
if we do all this and get these talented
women back in full
form in the workforce who knows what
will be possible next
thank you so much for your time
[Music]
[Applause]
i'm super excited for our next guest
speakers who will be sharing what it
means to have the courage to create
space for others to rise
welcome lindawi and carrie
[Music]
hello all and thank you so much for
joining us for this session today i'm
super excited because
i am with one of my partners and we are
going to be
talking a little bit about the courage
to create space for others to rise
my name is lynn dowey david hi i'm
carrie yen
and a little bit about me i am a
diversity equity and inclusion program
manager lead
working at google i specifically work
within an engineering organization
driving co-leading strategy alignment
around how we can increase
the culture within the org include
sentiment
increase feelings of of inclusiveness
but also having programming that
works for everyone to show up to and
build that education awareness around
a little bit about my background i'm a
program
program manager on the federated
security team
under privacy safety and security where
i lead the efforts
on our community and engagement work
stream as well as the operations for
our core team pretty delicious harry
um so i guess we're gonna jump right
into it you know when
when thinking about women rising and
what that means
to you right um what does that look like
within the past
five years of your life professionally
personally
um and what are you looking forward to
what it looks like
for women rising especially for myself
in the past
five years you know it really has
shifted
especially due to covid and i think
right now there are expectations
and unrealistic expectations when it
comes
for females and how we're viewed we are
supposed to
be acting a certain way we're supposed
to be
dressing a certain way and presenting
ourselves and behaving a certain way
and we're living up to these standards
that are unrealistic
you put that right on the nail right i
think about
what it means to rise right just in your
professional career
there's all of these um check boxes
right that we feel like we have to
adhere to um
a lot of the times you know we don't
meet those check boxes
uh either those social constructions
that's been placed on us but also
the ones that we place on ourselves we
start to feel like
we're failing right but the last five
years for me
has really meant that um i've been
flexible
right in the rise to where i am today
because my background is in
finance and marketing and publishing and
um
branding etc but how i've gotten to
google
and beyond right with some of the
projects and things that i'm involved in
um has been a direct result of being
flexible does that
kind of resonate with you as well
absolutely especially when you touch
point about checking the box i think
probably five years ago i felt that i
had a laundry list of accomplishments
that i needed to hit before
specific milestones to please
actually those around me and also
society as well
there's a stereotype that women need to
have
that white picket fence the 2.5 kids
that they need to be the overall
caretaker and also um
and also excel and at work as well
professionally and um
reflecting back especially recently
i've accepted that i don't need to check
that box and that i've
had to learn and grow that i can look at
my imperfections perfectly
and the number one thing that i have
learned in the past five years
is that i need to take care of myself
because
i'm a caretaker for for my loved ones as
well
for my parents um and
it's important for me to not only take
care of myself
physically but also mentally as well
because if i don't have a stable
foundation
um i won't be able to take care of those
around me as well
yeah and that also affects the rise you
just dropped an amazing gym right
with the whole um accepting the that
imperfections
perfectly oh man that's a that's a whole
line right there
so you know when we talked about
professionally um what are some
realizations that you've had working in
tech
for example you know any examples and
then also
what has shaped your approach on how you
navigate through those environments
in a predominantly male space being in
tech
now this is a deep one and we could
probably be here uh all day
right we've got volumes just between the
two of us
but um some of the realizations that
i've had is
a lot of times you feel like you're in
survival mode right when you're working
in
any professional space that is
predominantly male
um and most certainly when you are a
person of color
right like the navigation uh tools are
not always as clear
and so you had touched on this or was
getting ready to touch on this that it's
important to have like that network or
tribe of people
um who kind of just roll with you right
along
on your journey these folks can be
professionals these can be friends it
could be family
but um one of my strongest realizations
is that
um a lot of times you feel like you're
in survival mode and then the second
thing is that you've got to have a tribe
of people that you travel with
as you're rising in your in your career
absolutely i've learned um the hard way
actually
really it's very very important to have
advocates around you
and to also surround yourself with those
that will also uplift you and empower
you as well
so absolutely i love it i love that
speaking of that kind of touches on this
next segment right but we're kind of
talking through our own personal power
how do you recognize your personal power
when did you recognize it
and how has it carried you through your
career
my personal power is
this joke within information security
it's
the stereotype that every all of us are
special snowflakes
that's my part that is my personal power
um
i realize that i am unique i don't
check all the boxes and i don't have
that traditional background
that those in my profession
do as well and that's what makes me
unique and a special snowflake i can
come in with a different perspective
and doesn't mean it needs to be 100
right all the time
but with that with a different
perspective encourages
and gives an opportunity for
collaboration and innovation as well
so curious what's your what's your uh
i think with my personal power man i
am someone who's able to take like quiet
spectators into
full-on participants uh in various
situations and various projects
and because i work in the diversity
equity and inclusion space
it's um you have to have that kind of
personal power within you to be that
pathway builder
and a person who has a high level of
diplomacy as well
and so those things have always kind of
carried me through
uh even when i was facing uh
i'll call them nemesis from the past uh
because as a as a woman working in tech
and just being a professional for as
long as i've been
there's always been some nemesis or
barrier that has jumped out of somewhere
and i've had to tap into my level of
diplomacy and how i speak to people
right so they understand how to respect
me but also so that they understand that
um either way you cut it i'm going to
rise above
all absolutely
i i can't uh i can't agree with you more
on your last statement
yeah very curious has there ever been a
defining moment in your life
that you put on a path to understand
your
personal power more oh um
i think when i think about when i was a
kid there's so many
there were so many moments like i you
know i had the kind of mother who was
very
um very much in education very much
interested in making sure she let
myself and my brothers know that you
know you can live this
life and uh live it in a way that's
filled with a lot of honor and a lot of
integrity
and um mistakes as well
and the biggest thing one of the biggest
things she taught us was around like
picking up for yourself
right which is where that level of
diplomacy i think started for me and
that started way back when i was
probably 12
maybe 12 13 years old and um we were
leaving
the uh we were coming from new york they
are not originally from new york but
this is where i'm stationed right now
and so when i was a kid i lived here
for a little bit of time and we ended up
moving to
the west coast in arizona and uh
what's interesting about that is that
when i head to transfer schools
they the schools that i was going to at
the time trying to put me into some sort
of reading class
right and i had already tested out of
reading i was
you know an honor student um and was a
bit more advanced
and so i spoke up and said listen i'm
not supposed to be in the class
and no one believed me so then i my
mother what was going on
my mother went down to school and there
was a bit of a back and forth but
ultimately
they took me out of the class to put me
in the
advanced class that i had already tested
after that but it taught me that
right off the bat you have to think for
yourself and you have to know
where you are in your life and at 12
years old i had a level of
self-awareness that was very strong
about where i was going
thank you so much for sharing that story
and making yourself vulnerable
that that's such a great story speaking
about childhood
one thing that comes into mind is
actually
my grandmother so it took me
probably moving in my 20s going to
school and starting off my career to
really reflect back
and really understand her power
and her personal struggles as well
coming from hong kong
and leaving her life to come over and to
immigrate over to america
to help support my parents as well i
think about that
um especially when i was in college too
and
just trying to
just navigate through life in my 20s
and always wanting to in a way yeah to
quit
and you realize reflecting back that how
much the struggles is
thinking how my grandmother had to learn
how to navigate through a new world
in a language that she didn't know in a
culture and customs that she wasn't
aware of
with all of those amazing experiences
and
you know between the two of us i imagine
we could write a book
right uh some sort of graphic novel or
uh uh theories you know with a mainstay
character
but how have some of those positive
experiences that you've had in your life
through all of that absorption right
from the time you were a kid up until
now
um impacted others and how do you want
to continue to kind of impact people
in their you know climb to uh where they
want to go
yeah one thing that comes into mind is
that pay it forward
um mindset i think of those in the past
um that have been advocates and for
mentors to me that have guided me
that have watched me take a path
where i didn't succeed but they still
stood by me
and they knew that ultimately in the end
that i would learn
and grow as an individual professionally
and personally
um through those situations as well and
i reflect back it's important to pay it
forward as well
so that's why when i mentioned earlier
that advocacy
and making sure that you have allies and
a strong network
are surrounded by you is so important
yeah i i'm a big fan of advocacy and
mentorship
and sponsorship right those three things
they fall within the same
family but for me i um when it comes to
like all of those experiences and all
that wisdom that i've just been
absorbing
throughout my years as a professional um
i always let people know right away that
you know when you're trying to get from
point a to point b
you have to be very honest about you
know where you're trying to go
you have to be honest about where you
are as a person as well
and be and think to yourself listen i
can do this thing
right and if this thing doesn't work out
for me if this one little thing doesn't
work out for me
i'm not gonna stop i'm gonna go to the
next thing
right and figure out how uh i can take
myself from
that one little failure that resulted in
me trying
to me trying again and using the wisdom
that i picked up from that previous
quote unquote failure
um that's a little bit of that wisdom
that i always kind of give to younger
people
but most certainly to other women as
well just to kind of open up the hope
factor right
uh the hope factor as i call it it's
probably called something else
in other circles but um i typically
refer to it as like my hope factor or my
hope tank and i'm like
get in the business of making sure that
your whole tank is super full
because the ride is not easy right when
you're on the rise that's not meant to
be
because otherwise you didn't really earn
it right so
uh that's typically how i take like
whether the
experience was positive whether it was a
negative experience whether it was a
failure
what have you i take all of that and i
give it to people in a way that it's
tangible
for them to understand that um i'm here
for you
and that i'm a human being just like you
and sitting in this seat
right was not an easy feat in any way
shape or form
absolutely um i love your comment about
the hope tank as well i
if you don't mind i'm going to take that
yeah
and um i think it's really important too
that we need to look at those
with the vulnerabilities and also
embrace it as well and then
also share our losses i think
that we do live in a world where women
have to
[Music]
live in perfection and and whatnot we
don't talk about the stories where
there was failure there were nights
where you know whether
you want to cry in a pillow scream in a
pillow
crying shower um yeah and i think just
being raw and authentic
and telling those stories as well can
help others
and next generations grow professionally
like you said
it took a lot for both of us to get here
and to be in these chairs it was not an
overnight success as well there were so
many barriers
um and um and so much struggle as well
but
knowing that they are not the only ones
struggling
and so that there is a time and that
there's a path for them as well
yeah i think that that's spot on like
there's no uh there's no easy way
you know to the top right and you can
try to take the elevator
feel free feel free but the elevator's
gotta stop
at some point it's got to stop on this
floor it's got to stop on the fifth
floor it's gotta
you know continuously stop and so
i think there's a level of patience that
kind of attached to that too
um as like if you're on the elevator and
you're in a certain position and a door
open
rolling with this analogy and we see a
younger person coming up or just another
person who has
made the decision to change their life
and they get on the elevator
why not give them that additional space
right um
to feel a bit more comfortable uh that's
kind of how i put it into practice like
i i want people to feel like
when they come and talk to me for
example that they
are talking to someone who not only has
the experience
to back up what i'm saying but i also
have there's a level of wisdom that
comes with
being of a certain age right and then
there's another layer of that
i also happen to be a poc i'm this
amazing black woman walking around
uh and there are so many things to
consider
as a result of walking around in this
vessel that i'm in
that i'm super proud of but there are
other people who
may not be in this building so i want to
create space for them as well
um to have that kind of collaboration
and camaraderie
um and for us to remember that and for
everybody to remember that don't believe
the hype that women do not
hype up each other i haifa akari uh uh
kerry i should say um i have all kinds
of people on a regular basis because it
just comes natural to me i'm not missing
out on anything by doing so
absolutely it is so important to
advocate and also empower and also hype
up those
other females as well thank you
for sure so talking a little bit about
accountability
right uh this is a word that's just been
flying around
uh you know especially i think last year
there were so
many things that happen so many
atrocities
um and the the the
amount of violence that continues just
in general whether it's against women
uh black plus both um lgbtq
community asian plus folks like there is
always something going on and to
consider and so
the word accountability really continues
to kind of pop
up right um especially in professional
spaces so i think um
i wanna i want us to kind of talk about
how do we plug accountability
into this picture of making sure that
we're giving space
to um you know other women to rise as
well like
what do you think the pathway to being
more accountable looks like
if you're a manager or even if you're an
individual contributor
absolutely you know there's small little
tactical things that i actually do on an
everyday basis
i make sure to
cultivate my relationships with the
other females within security as well to
really understand them as a person
and then also them professionally as
well so that when i'm in a meeting
i can actually speak up on their behalf
and give them the
opportunity to also voice their opinion
it's simple other things as well when
you notice a meeting invite and it is
heavily male dominated
um call it out i i sure have um
you know just asking just like you know
what i also think that
so and so would be um appropriate to be
in this meeting uh does it make sense to
add them
even as optional i love that carrie
i love that i think the speaking up part
is the thing that resonates
with me that instead of waiting for
things to kind of
boil over or be swept under the rug you
got to call that stuff out right away
i want to add some things to that list
which is
it does not hurt anyone to have a little
bit more empathy
right like absolutely to just employ
empathy in your
everyday life but most certainly when it
comes to professionalism
i think that the empathy like lifting up
your level of empathy and understanding
of that
will also take your listening skills up
a level as well
right because a lot of times we're we're
all trying to tell these stories we want
to make sure that we're acknowledged
in the work that we're doing but a lot
of times the work
may get you know swept under the rug
because people are not listening
and uh to your point people are not in
the room when they should be in the room
so something that i typically like to do
i want to make sure that people get the
credit for the work that they're doing
i want to speak up on behalf of folks
who are not in the room
and i also want to make sure that i
speak up for myself because that's like
the
big thing right it's not just enough to
have your
you know your um sponsors and your
mentors and
your advocates in the room dropping your
name you know from time to time but you
yourself have to believe
that you're meant to be in that room as
well
absolutely and it's being proud of your
work as well
even though i had an issue and this is
still
something that i'm trying and struggling
with is that i
need to be very proud of all my work
whether i think it's a small tactical
aspect
no it actually makes huge impact it does
whether
i think and i will downplay it um as
something small and minor it does it
makes impact
org wide or um and also companies why
company-wide as well yeah that's that's
a true story
true story like i feel like like we're
in such a position like if you if you're
someone who has finally made it to a
quote-unquote
uh place of privilege when you typically
are not
known to have privilege um i just heard
this from
uh another uh panel that i was involved
in where
uh the question was you know you're a
black plus
woman how do you um how do you see
yourself now that you have a smidge of
privilege working
in the tech space doing the work that i
do and so
my thought about that was that's
interesting
because in my real life i you know
i'm not privileged per se but i do work
extremely hard
right and because i'm now sitting in the
seat that i'm sitting in
i use that seat every chance i get every
chance i get
to uh talk to as many young people as i
need to
mentor raise my hand and not just raise
my hand but actually
action take actionable step behind the
raising of the hands
and i think that there's a lot of times
like i see uh
in whether it's in tech or in other
industries where
you know there's a lot of people who are
you know raising their hand to do
certain things
but that's not the same thing as taking
action so i think that if we want to
continue to kind of create that space
for women
um and and i do mean all women right
uh people of color uh
are underrepresented groups black plus
latinx plus our indigenous folks
uh our uh lgbtq community etc
if we want to continue to kind of make
sure that uh folks feel like
they're a part of an entire tribe
working together
um and rising together there is
something to be said about making sure
that we can activate but actually
understanding that we uh are moving
in the same direction because that's
super important
absolutely gosh what you just said is so
just so inspiring right now i'm just i
just feel so empowered
so thank you thank you
yes thank you no i appreciate you carrie
what what let's close this out what is
the last
um what was the last thing you thought
about in 2020 that you wanted to change
right and what are you looking forward
to this year in terms of
uh assisting and helping women
to their next step reflecting back on
i looked at it as a very check the box i
had that mentality
and up until probably towards the end of
i realized that life is like a marathon
i go at my own pace and as a from as a
former ultra marathon runner
i needed to listen to my own words
because
no matter what situation it is
everything is like a marathon
you can train for it you can
you can get your pr you can train for it
and
um you can get the time that you maybe
didn't desire
you cannot train and you can injure
yourself
um there's many consequences but it's
important that everybody goes at their
own pace
any runner will tell you to when they're
going when they're running they'll look
at people next to them
you don't know their story i
like i said i am a former ultra marathon
runner
and i am also
someone that has been in marathons
before and i looked at someone
who was i had a good 30 plus years on my
age and i was just like i don't
understand but
i need to scale back and remember that i
don't know their story
i don't know if it's how long they've
been training i don't know if they're
injury prone at all and so
i had to in a way check myself and yeah
i think that's something that
understanding that life is a marathon
was something that really
really hit hard for 2020 on me yeah
so in 2021 i actually really want to
spread that message and spread that word
to other females as well and hope they
understand
that we do not need to be perfect we
are super women we do so much there's
unrealistic expectations on us and it's
okay
to take a jogging pace it is okay to
walk the marathon
because at the end all of us get the
medal
all of us get the bagels the bananas at
the end
and all of us all of us cross the finish
line we need to just go at our own pace
i got all the snaps on that one yes yes
yes yes
i listen when i think about 2020 i think
about
uh this level of feeling like you're
imperfect
right because now you know for the year
you were at home
uh some of us had our kids at home some
of us were by ourselves
some of us had our partners uh you know
et cetera et cetera there was so there's
so many layers to explore
but the one thing that kind of kept
coming back to me that is that we were
missing that component of togetherness
right because we didn't have our jobs to
go too physically
right and we spend what most of our days
free close it
we spent most of our days with the
people that we worked with
right and so once that was taken away we
were back in our houses
and with all of those varied situations
there was time to kind of think about
how important it is to be together
right uh whether it's with your
co-workers who you
deeply respect and you have friendships
with whether it's with your family
whether it's with friends whether it's
with your kids whether it's with your
partner
um whether it's with your own thought i
think that that right there was
something that was very glaring to me
uh last year and then when i bring that
thinking into this year and how
that is super important to me i just
keep thinking about how
you really have to remember to speak up
for yourself
and in doing so it makes it easier for
you to speak up for others
right i touched on this earlier where
it's kind of like
when you have a strong level of
self-awareness about who you are as a
person where you're going
what your goals are what your strengths
are uh it's super easy
i think to uh speak to other people
and help them find their way through
that as well right
but also to amplify that uh i think it
actually it takes nothing off of you to
um send somebody some sort of
recommendation or reference when they
reach out to you
and you might know about their work
right it doesn't take
some large amount of energy for you to
reach out to someone and just check on
them and make sure that they're doing
okay
that's both personally and
professionally so
the thing i really want to bring into
the year and want to keep that going
is just like the level of togetherness
um
figuring out creative ways to uh be
impactful to someone's life that's
useful
uh which is the third thing that i think
about i don't want to sit here and worry
about the things that i cannot change
i want to think about what's useful to
me and then also
how is that going to also help other
people once i go through the situation
as well
absolutely well
this has been a delicious conversation
carrie uh
i want to thank everyone for tuning in
to this session um
we appreciate you so much we've enjoyed
our time
and much like carrie has said much like
i
said just remember that you have space
uh
on this planet to be who you really want
to be and live the life you want to live
thank you so much thanks everyone
[Music]
[Applause]
all right welcome back to the main track
as we are
closing the day out we would like to
share some other
regional summits happening around the
world for you to join
you can see the dates and countries that
are listed on the screen
find the links of the summit on our
website shown on the slide
and also in our follow-up emails since
you registered for this event
hopefully you will enjoy all of the
regional summit if you enjoyed this one
too
with that said let's just wrap up this
event
well thank you so much for supporting
iwd north america summit and choosing to
spend these last two wonderful days
here with us we hope you all enjoyed
and were inspired by the talks learnings
and discussions
of this huge summit we would like to
extend a big thanks to our wonderful
speakers
and our amazing team who helped put this
event together
we appreciate you all for joining us in
this moment towards equality
and let's continue to pledge towards a
my more
diverse and inclusive world don't forget
to share your feedback with
us from the link on the screen you will
get a chance to win one of the awesome
raffle prizes
and lastly take care and have a great
rest of your weekend
you